<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iacobs wel, and Abbots conduit paralleled, preached, and applied (in the cathedrall and metropoliticall Church of Christ in Canterbury) to the vse of that citie; now to make glad the citie of God. By Iames Cleland, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Cleland, James, d. 1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856426</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856426</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1093:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iacobs wel, and Abbots conduit paralleled, preached, and applied (in the cathedrall and metropoliticall Church of Christ in Canterbury) to the vse of that citie; now to make glad the citie of God. By Iames Cleland, Doctor of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Cleland, James, d. 1627.</author>
                  <author>Pass, Simon van de, 1595?-1647, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 53, [3] p., plate : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Robert Allot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved.</note>
                  <note>The frontispiece is an engraved portrait of George Abbot signed: Simon Passæus sculp: Lond:.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Abbot, George, 1562-1633.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Quam b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne clare Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, deſignant nomina vita</l>
               <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na tuam, nom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n quam bent vita tuum?<note place="margin">Simon Paſsaeus ſculp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lond:</note>
               </l>
               <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m quòd ſis fidus divini cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tor age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i</l>
               <l>Agrico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ê ſirimo nomine nomen haſse<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>niam Anglorum Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doctiſsime Pateum</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ius ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artem nominis Abba dedit</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>coris cus Tos, ingentioz i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as ô titulis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Abbate diane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uis.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IACOBS WELL And ABBOTS CONDVIT</hi> Paralleled Preached, and Applied, To the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Citie of Canterbury. <hi>BY IAMES CLELAND D.D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Printed at London for Robert Allot</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:2"/>
            <p>IACOBS WEL, AND ABBOTS CONDVIT, Paralleled, Preached, and Applied (In the Cathedrall and Metropoliticall CHVRCH of CHRIST in CANTERBVRY) <hi>To the</hi> VSE <hi>of</hi> that <hi>Citie;</hi> now to make glad the <hi>Citie</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY IAMES CLELAND, <hi>Doctor of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>S. <hi>IOHN 7.37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>IESVS</hi> ſtood, and cryed, ſaying, If any man thirſt, let him come vnto me, and drinke.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>IESVS</hi> ſaid, If I waſh thee not, thou haſt not part with me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:3"/>
            <head>REVERENDISSIMO IN CHRISTO PATRI, D. GEOEGIO ABBA TO, <hi>Diuina Prouidentia,</hi> Archiepiſcopo <hi>Cantuarienſi,</hi> totius <hi>Angliae</hi> Primati &amp; Metropolitae, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giaeque Majeſtati, à Secretio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus <hi>Conſilijs, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>IACOBVS CLELANDVS</hi> Scotus, Hoc Grati Animi Monumentum ponebat.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>APIENTISSI MVS REX SALOMON, alijque Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri Prudentes quàmplures, (ARCHI-PRAESVL AMPLISSIME) qui la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes &amp; abditas rerum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalium cauſas inquiruut, fluminum perennes ortus, fontiumque ſcaturigines Oceano referunt, inque eundem Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num
<pb facs="tcp:21975:4"/>aquas refluere, &amp; naturali velut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petu remeare monent. Nec mirum hoc cuiquam vidcatur, cùm conſonum ſit ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni, experientiae, Sacris Literis, &amp; Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Philoſophorum. Ex limpidis enim Fontibus, ſtrepentes oriuntur amnes; ex amnibus, torrentes rapidi; ex torrenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus fluuij ſeraces; fluuijque in Oceanum plenis exuberant oſtijs; vnde primùm per varios terrae meatus promanarunt. Eſt quippè rerum omnium quidam velut or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, vt cuncta vnde deriuantur, huc per vices reuerti naturalis ratio deſideret. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudens ego itaque &amp; ingratus fuerim, ſi <hi>Fontes hos</hi> alterius nomini aut numini, quàm <hi>Tuo</hi> offerrem &amp; dicarem, vt qui <hi>Te</hi> potiſſimùm iactant <hi>Authorem, Tibi</hi> reddan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Ac velut aquae magno illo Mari emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae Oceanum ipſum repetunt; ita <hi>Fontes iſti,</hi> in <hi>Te</hi> ſpontaneo induſtriae meae Voto refluant. Ingratus ego in quam, quia be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificentiae <hi>Tuae Fontes, non minùs aduenis, quam indigenis,</hi> gratis patent, &amp; inter <hi>illos, mihi</hi> praecipue riguo fluxu aſpergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem perennem effundunt. Quaprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iam quod à Priſcis in dedicatione quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundam Monumentorum, memoriſque animi teſtificatione vſurpatum eſt, LV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BENS
<pb facs="tcp:21975:4"/>MERITOQVE, <hi>Fontes hos (Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentiae Tuae)</hi> cum maximis gratijs repono. Neque ego tantùm, ſed vniuerſi etiam &amp; ſinguli, non horum modò, ſed futurorum aliquando temporum <hi>Ciues Cantuarienſes,</hi> hoc <hi>Tibi Beneficium</hi> acceptum referent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendetque gratias vnuſquiſque &amp; ſuo, &amp; <hi>Ciuitatis</hi> nomine nunquam intermoritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras. <hi>Ciuitas</hi> denique ipſa <hi>Cantuaria,</hi> tanti <hi>Beneficij</hi> gratijs rependendis iam impar, vel hoc nomine ingenue profitetur, vt conſcia ſuae tenuitatis, non voluntatem ſibi, aut memoriam <hi>Beneficij Tui</hi> (<hi>Fontis</hi> vtpote) ſed facultatem referendi deeſſe. Sicque SVMME ANTISTES,</p>
            <q>
               <l>In freta dum fluuii current, dum montibus vmbrae</l>
               <l>Luſtrabunt, conuexa polus dum ſidera paſcet,</l>
               <l>Semper honos, nomenque tuum, laudeſque manebunt.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21975:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Chriſtian and curteous Reader, Ahijah</hi> the Prophet, taking hold of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> new garment, rent it in twelue pieces<note n="a" place="margin">1. Kings, 11.30.</note>. <hi>Elijah</hi> ſermoned on the little barrell of meale, and cruſe of oyle of his Hoſteſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Widow of Zarephath</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Kings, 17.4.</note>. And his Scholler <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ha</hi> did the like preaching vpon the pitcher of oyle of the <hi>Shunamite Woman</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Kings, 4.7.</note>. By theſe viſible ſignes the Prophets would more deeply print their meſſage into their hearts to whom they were ſent. So our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> ſitting on <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> tooke a fit occaſion to giue the <hi>Woman of Samaria</hi> a taſte of that Spirituall Water of life<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note>. Whereof he himſelfe is the euerlaſting and vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted <hi>Fountaine,</hi> in asking of her but common water. After theſe examples, eſpecially this of our good and great <hi>Doctor Chriſt,</hi> at first when I ſaw my <hi>Lord Arch-Biſhops Conduit in Canterburie,</hi> and being intreated then to preach in the <hi>Cathedrall Church of Chriſt</hi> there, I choſe <hi>Iacobs Well</hi> for my <hi>Text,</hi> and drew deepe, bringing out hence more then ordinarie and vulgar Water. Wherefore I hope that I cannot ſeeme, or be taxed by any ſound iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to haue fetcht water out of mine owne braine vnto this Text, nor from the words thereof to wring out bloud, by forcing them, following ſo good a pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne. Howſoeuer, who is a thirſt, or would be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, let him come to drinke and waſh himſelfe <hi>thus at Iacobs Well,</hi> in aſſurance;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Limpidius nihil eſt, Lector, nil alſius iſto</l>
               <l>Fonte leuare ſitim, ſiue lauare iuuat.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21975:5"/>
            <head>IACOBS WELL, AND ABBOTS CONDVIT, Paralleled, Preached, and Applied <hi>To the vſe of the Citie of</hi> CANTERBVRIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>S. IOHN c. 4. v. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now Jacobs Well was there.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Patriarch Iacob</hi> after his<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 33.18.</note> 
               <hi>twentie yeeres ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice with his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle Laban, when he came from Padan-Aram, and pitched his Tent before the Citie of Sychar, there hee bought a parcell of a field, wherein he digged this Well,</hi> and gaue it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21975:6"/>that Citie. IESVS in his ſecond going vnto Galilee,<note n="b" place="margin">Multum ille &amp; terris iacta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus &amp; alto, Quae regio in terris <hi>Chriſti</hi> non plena labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Aeneid. <hi>1.</hi> princ.</note> 
               <hi>being wearied with his journey, ſate thus on this Well, to make glad the Citie of God.</hi> Not long agoe, our <hi>Arch-Patriarch</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abbas</hi> qui praeeſſe dignus eſt Eccleſiae, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per meminiſſe debet quod dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; nomen <hi>Maioris,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Superioris</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis implere, <hi>Chriſti</hi> enim vices gerere in Eccleſia credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quando ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias vecatur praenomine, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente Apoſtolo, Accipiſtis Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum adoptionis filiorum in quo cla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amus <hi>Abba Pater.</hi> Gregor. Mag.</note> 
               <hi>Abbots,</hi> at his ſecond comming into <hi>Kent,</hi> erected a coſtly <hi>Conduit</hi> heere, and beſtowed it <hi>vnto the vſe of this Citie of Canterburie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe three <hi>Founders</hi> or <hi>Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,</hi> together with their charitable <hi>works</hi> or <hi>Wells,</hi> are briefely comprehended in this little ſentence I haue read vnto you, and all theſe in a<note n="d" place="margin">Spiritu San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto factum eſt, vt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae locus mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſenſibus ſit ſoecundus. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin. l. 2. de Chriſtiana do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina.</note> threefold ſenſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is concerning <hi>Iacob,</hi> and his <hi>Well,</hi> in the<note n="e" place="margin">Litera geſta docet; quid cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das myſterium: Analogia quid agas.</note> letter. The ſecond is of IESVS, and as he is the <hi>Fountaine of life,</hi> theſe two myſtically; and ſo <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> 
               <hi>Jacobs Ladder ſet vpon the earth, and the top of it reaching vnto Heauen;</hi> or vnto<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid.</hi> 30.37.</note> 
               <hi>Iacobs Haſel-rods partly pilled, and partly couered.</hi> Our third ſenſe is of my <hi>Lord Arch-Biſhop,</hi> and of <hi>his Conduit,</hi> by analogie, or proportion with <hi>Iacobs Well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To parallell theſe <hi>two</hi> chiefly, I haue choſen this <hi>Text,</hi> at this <hi>Time,</hi> and in this <hi>Place;</hi> and to proceed methodically, we muſt beginne at the <hi>Letter;</hi> Wherein wee may obſerue theſe <hi>fiue occurrences,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21975:6"/>to the number of words of my <hi>Text,</hi> and conforme to ſo<note n="h" place="margin">[Struct tra Georgij D. Archiepiſcopi C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntuar. In vſum Ciuitatis Cantuariae. Ann. Dom. 1621.]</note> many ſhort lines, grauen for <hi>Title</hi> or <hi>Inſcription</hi> on the <hi>Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpice of your Conduit.</hi> Firſt is <hi>Structura,</hi> the Worke it ſelfe, <hi>[a Well:]</hi> the ſecond is the <hi>Founder [Iacob:]</hi> the third is the <hi>Place, [There:]</hi> the fourth is the <hi>Time, [Was:]</hi> fiſt and laſt is, <hi>In vſum Ciuitatis,</hi> which I referre to this particle <hi>[Now;]</hi> ſeeing.<note n="i" place="margin">Singuli ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones, ſyllabae, apices, puncia in Diuina Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura plena ſunt ſenſibus Hieron. in cap. 3. Epheſ. Non apices, non literae, non ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bae, non verba, non nomina in Euangelio diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis vacua ſunt myſterijs. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Chriſol. ſerm. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Gods holy Word, there is no ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous jod, euery title or circumſtance hath ſome pith, and ſerues to ſome good vſe and purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As in theſe fiue ſmall words, conſider firſt <hi>Situm,</hi> (according to the rules of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecture) the <hi>Site</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Jacobs Well,</hi> modelled, or rather folded vp in this locall demonſtratiue, <hi>[There:]</hi> yet expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated more at large for Hiſtorie and Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie, before and after my <hi>Text.</hi> For firſt the <hi>Place</hi> is bounded out, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terjacent betweene <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Galile</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Inter duos montes, Bethel ſcil &amp; Dan, ſitae eſt ciuitas Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem, quae hodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Neapolis voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, amoenitate &amp; delitus nullo loco inſerior. Haud longe à porta Auſtrali eſt iſte <hi>Fons Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> in via quae dacit Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Brocard in deſcrip. Terrae Sanctae. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>, in the midway betweene them both. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the name of the Shire was <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and of the <hi>Citie Sychar,</hi> which was a <hi>chiefe Citie</hi> of that <hi>Countrie.</hi> Thirdly, the Vicinitie or Neighbourhood of it, is laid downe, as being neere vnto the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that <hi>Iacob</hi> gaue to his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21975:7"/>Fourthly, and laſtly is deſcribed by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of our ſweet <hi>Sauiour</hi> from his owne Countrie and Countrie-men, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this way of<note n="l" place="margin">De hoc conſilio &amp; propoſito ſuo vide Rupert. &amp; Cyrillum lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Ioh. c. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> purpoſe, <hi>to drinke of the Brooke for his refection,</hi> and refreſhing of others, as was<note n="m" place="margin">De torrente in via bibens. <hi>Pſal. 110.7.</hi>
               </note> prophecied.</p>
            <p>Where by the way,<note n="n" place="margin">Auguſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us praeclarè ſerm. <hi>92</hi> de Temp. Praedium, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit,</hi> non tam Ioſepho, quàm Chriſto arbitror derelictum, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ſiguram S. Ioſeph Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha portauit, quem verè Sol adorat, &amp; Luna &amp; omnes Stellae benedicunt. Ad hoc praedium ideo venit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, vt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritani, qui haereditatem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi Patriarchae Iſrael vendicare cupiebart, ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcerent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſorem ſuum, &amp; conuerteren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad Chriſtum, qui legitimus Patriarchae hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res eſt factus.</note> obſerue that Prophecie made of <hi>Iacob</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> is more liuely verified in <hi>Ieſus,</hi> than in <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe: <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 49.22.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall be as a fruitfull branch by the Well ſide;</hi> when neuer did <hi>Ioſeph</hi> take perſonall poſſeſſion in this place, but by<note n="p" place="margin">Hebr. 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>Faith,</hi> or by tranſlation of his bones, and in his poſteritie; and they alas! how often interrupted, and at the laſt, as now, quite exterminated. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this was <hi>Iacobs</hi> purchaſe, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> inheritance, by <hi>promiſe,</hi> by <hi>legacie,</hi> by <hi>prophecie</hi> conformed to the faithfull; yet beſide the ſacking of this Citie of <hi>Sychar</hi> by <hi>Iacobs ſonnes,</hi> and the abandoning of the ſame by <hi>Iacob himſelfe,</hi> it was<note n="q" place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> firſt freed by that ambitious bramble <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> then the whole Region being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by the caluiſh Religion of<note n="r" place="margin">1. King. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> in defection whereof this <hi>Citie</hi> was ſuddenly<note n="ſ" place="margin">1. King. 12.25.</note> deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I wrap vp this briefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21975:7"/>of <hi>Place</hi> againe with theſe three notes. One is,<note n="t" place="margin">Sic omnia verti cernimus atque alias aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere robora Gentes, &amp;c. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. <hi>2.</hi> Clara fuit Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta: magnae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guere Mycenae, Neenon &amp; Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cropis, neenon Amphionis ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Ouid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> that there is no certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of continuall proſperitie in the moſt ſetled <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the World, whereof let <hi>Sychem</hi> and <hi>Samaria</hi> bee witneſſes: or if theſe be not ſufficient proofs, as being of a too ancient date &amp; of a too diſtant abode from vs,<note n="u" place="margin">Quocunque aſpicio, nihil eſt niſi pontus &amp; aër, fluctibus hic tumidus, nubibus ille mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nax. &amp;c. idem. Vide Valer. Max. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Ammian. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Sabellic. de ſubita fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuna. li. <hi>7.</hi> Apul. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Metam. cicero de Nat. Deor. Boët. lib. <hi>2</hi> de conſol. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa <hi>2.</hi> &amp; Plin. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>40.</hi> prae cateris elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</note> then looke round about our <hi>Neighbour Countries</hi> at this inſtant, as in Germanie, the Palatinate, &amp;c. and you ſhall ſee how the <hi>Cities</hi> and whole <hi>Shyres</hi> there are perſecuted, harroſed and diſpeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled. Although we dwell ſafely and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, (praiſed be God) euery man vnder his Vine and Fig-tree, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Berſheba,</hi> from <hi>Kent</hi> to <hi>Kentyre,</hi> from the <hi>South of England,</hi> to the <hi>North of Scotland,</hi> yet let no man pretend to exempt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from miſeries but through the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God. Thinke not our ſelues ſecure otherwiſe, becauſe wee liue in a mightie <hi>Land</hi> of two <hi>Nations;</hi> no, wee liue in an <hi>Iland,</hi> therefore in danger of the <hi>Sea;</hi> in a <hi>Chriſtian Iland,</hi> therefore in danger of the <hi>Turke;</hi> in a <hi>Proteſtant Iland,</hi> therefore in danger of the <hi>Pope;</hi> in a <hi>Chiefe Citie</hi> of the <hi>Iland,</hi> therefore in danger of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</hi> For mightineſſe of State, frequencie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21975:8"/>of ſtrangers, multitude of people, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſſe of arts, heapes of riches, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſneſſe of buildings, ſtore of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſtrength of munition, make Cities ſettle vpon their lees, and yet not they, but their abuſes.<note n="u" place="margin">Ezech. 16.33.</note> 
               <hi>O harlot Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Nahum 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>O blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Niniueb!</hi> they be the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>Ezechiel</hi> and <hi>Nahum: Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus, Lais</hi> at <hi>Corinth, Mahomet</hi> at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, Anti-chriſt</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> but here at <hi>Canterburie, omniabenè.</hi> Farre bee it from me to forget the honour of this <hi>Citie;</hi> as the <hi>Spirit</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Church of Thiatira,</hi> Reuel. 2.20. and as<note n="y" place="margin">Ego cum Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto, qui affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mauit ſe faciliùs paſſurum detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi aliquid, quàm Ciuitatis Romanae vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gari honorem. Sueton. in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto cap. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſt.</hi> of the <hi>Citie</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet I muſt tell you, that as the great ſickneſſes,<note n="z" place="margin">Dedit hanc contagio labem &amp; dabit in plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> ſo the great ſinnes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily are from hence deriued to the Countrie.</p>
            <p>My ſecond note is,<note n="a" place="margin">Polibius. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din. de Repub. lib. <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Delicta qui non vetat, cum poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, iubet, Senec. Traged.</note> that ſinne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledged, and corruption of <hi>Religion</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed or wincked at, though but in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie,</hi> yet are they the bane and ruine of the moſt flouriſhing <hi>Common-wealths</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of the World. <hi>Who gaue Iacob for a ſpoile, and Iſrael to be robbed?</hi> Was it not the Lord, becauſe they had ſinned againſt him? <hi>And this thing became ſinne vnto the houſe of Ieroboam, euen to cut it off, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21975:8"/>it from off the face of the earth.</hi> 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 13.34. <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> may ſuffer di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of <hi>Languages,</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> of <hi>Policies,</hi> of <hi>Statutes</hi> in their <hi>States,</hi> becauſe they are but externall things, and concerne but mens outward actions, which change and varie according to the variety of occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, but they muſt beware of <hi>toleration</hi> or <hi>conniuency</hi> of <hi>falſe Religion</hi> without <hi>Gods</hi> iuſt iudgement againſt themſelues and their <hi>Kingdomes.</hi> For the Lord ſhall ſtrike through <hi>Kings</hi> in the day of his wrath; <hi>He ſhall iudge among the Heathen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 110.6.</note> 
               <hi>hee ſhall fill the place with the dead bodies; hee ſhall wound the heads ouer many great Countries;</hi> which are his foure puniſhments whereby he puniſheth his enemies. Pſal. 110.6.</p>
            <p>The third note is, that neither the <hi>Church of God inuiſibly,</hi> nor the Spirit illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating that <hi>Church infallibly,</hi> is bound to any <hi>Place, Citie,</hi> or <hi>Sea,</hi> there to <hi>reſide</hi> in the <hi>ſucceſsion of perſons:</hi> for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion was inhabited by <hi>Idolaters,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Oſe. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel</hi> became <hi>Bethauen, Turkes</hi> and <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> haue ſurpriſed the <hi>Holy-Land, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſitteth in the</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>Temple of God,</hi> the faithfull<note n="d" place="margin">Iſai. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>Citie</hi> is turned <hi>Harlot;</hi> in a word plainly,<note n="e" place="margin">Sanctus ager ſcurris, venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis, Ara cynae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis Seruit, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randae diuum Ganimed bus oedes, &amp;c. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuan de calam: ſuorum tempor. lib. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>393.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rome,</hi> is become <hi>Babylon,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21975:9"/>Leſt</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Nequis blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatur ſibi de lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c 9, Bern. ad Guil. Abb.</note> 
               <hi>any ſhould flatter themſelues in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent bolineſſe of the place.</hi> And thus wee leaue wandring at large about the <hi>Place,</hi> and ſettle our ſelues in view of a little <hi>Monument</hi> in the place, where our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour</hi> did vouchſafe to <hi>ſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> conſider, in this <hi>place</hi> there was a <hi>[Well]</hi> or a <hi>Spring:</hi> for euerie <hi>Well</hi> is a <hi>Spring,</hi> although euery <hi>Spring</hi> bee not a <hi>Well.</hi> A<note n="x" place="margin">Vbi de terra promanat aqua, ſi in promptu ſit at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuperficie, fons dicitur à fundendo: ſi autem in allo vel profundo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co; dicitur pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus, ſed ita, vt fontis nomen non amittat. Aug. tract. <hi>15.</hi> in Ioh.</note> 
               <hi>Spring</hi> or a <hi>Fountaine</hi> may bee <hi>in ſuperficie,</hi> eaſie to come by: A <hi>Well</hi> is <hi>in profundo,</hi> deepe to bee drawne at, and ſo was this. For as the <hi>Woman</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid, <hi>Puteus eſt profundus, the Well is deepe;</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Non comper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſuperbis, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nudata pueris; ſed quae inceſſu humilis, ſuceeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu excella, &amp; velata myſterijs, creſcit cum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulis, Aug. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Confeſſ. c. <hi>5.</hi> Diuinus ſermo, ſicut prudentes myſteriis exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet: ſie plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuperficie ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices refouet habet in publico vnde paruulos nutriat, ſeruat in ſecreto, vnde mentes ſublimiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> admiratione ſuſpendat. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. Epiſt. ad Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andr moral. in Ioh affix. fronti.</note> ſo it is indeed a <hi>Deepe,</hi> and yet a <hi>ſhallow ford,</hi> where the <hi>Lambe</hi> may wade, the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant</hi> ſwimme? therein are <hi>mysteries</hi> to exerciſe the wiſe, and <hi>Hiſtories</hi> to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the ſimple; z wherein not only the Learned may ſatisfie their deepe deſires, but alſo the ignorant may increaſe their knowledge.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, know the <hi>chiefe Founder</hi> of this <hi>Well</hi> or <hi>Fountaine</hi> was the <hi>Patriarch [Iacob]</hi> whoſe name was reuerendly rehearſed by the <hi>Samaritans</hi> at this <hi>Well,</hi> though they were ſtrangers to him, to his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> making onely a benefit of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21975:9"/>temporall commoditie; &amp; this his name, <hi>Iacob,</hi> will be remembred to the worlds end, whereſoeuer the <hi>Gospell</hi> ſhall bee <hi>Preached,</hi> as our Sauiour<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 26.13.</note> ſaid concerning the woman with the boxe of Oyntment. <hi>His name is like a good Oyntment</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ec. les. 71.</note> ſaith) the ſweet perfume whereof is not onely freſh and redolent at this preſent,<note n="c" place="margin">Multa viri virtus ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, multuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, recurſat Eius honos, haerent infixi pectore vultus.</note> but alſo ſhall bee for euer in this world, and in the World to come.</p>
            <p>Many there are who by carnal proiects as building and purchaſing for their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie, thinke to make their houſes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and their memories eternall, as <hi>Dauid</hi> well obſerueth, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 49.11. Theſe are like <hi>Nero,</hi> of whom the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">Erat eius ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitatis perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, famae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido ſed incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultè. Sueton-in vita Neron ca. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He did affect eternall fame, but he tooke no wiſe courſe to effect it.</hi> It is like <hi>Dauids</hi> cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the thirteenth verſe of that <hi>Pſalme, This their way vttereth their fooliſhneſſe.</hi> And no maruell, for <hi>God</hi> dealeth with them as the <hi>Epheſians</hi> dealt with <hi>Eroſtratus,</hi> who would be famous by burning the <hi>Temple of Diana;</hi> As they enacted a Law, that no man ſhould ſpeake of <hi>Eroſtratus,</hi> ſo Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie <hi>God</hi> enacteth a <hi>Law of obliuion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe carnall minded men, <hi>Their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21975:10"/>memoriall periſheth for euer.</hi> q Others are, who thinke to perpetuate their name and fame by erecting a Montiment of <hi>Marble, Braſſe,</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> when his life was rotten, as his corpſe after his death, and his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie can ſmel no ſweeter aboue ground, then his bodie vnder it. For who can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that a ſumptuous <hi>Tombe</hi> a painted <hi>Scutcheon,</hi> or a golden <hi>Epitaph</hi> can couer a putrified carcaſſe, when all that knew him will ſay, hee was a wicked man. Aſſure your ſelues,<note n="f" place="margin">Hoc enim v. num eſt, in relus humanis opus, cui nulla tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtas noceat, quod nulla con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumat vetuſtas: c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etera, quae per conſtructionem lapidum, &amp; marmore as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, aut terrenos tumulos in mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam educcos al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagahunt lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam diem: quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe &amp; ipſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunt, Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de conſol. ad Polyb. cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lt.</note> it is only a <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> and charitable <hi>good workes</hi> that make men attaine vnto true honour and memorie.<note n="g" place="margin">Impenſa mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti ſuperua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canea eſt, momo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria noſtra dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ſi vitam me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raimus, Eraſ. l. <hi>8.</hi> Apotheg.</note> A mans good life will moue euery mans heart to be his <hi>Tombe,</hi> and turneth euerie mans tongue into a Pen to write his deathleſſe <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As loe heere, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> by the pen of <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> hath regiſtred <hi>Iacobs</hi> name for beſtowing this benefit of his <hi>Well;</hi> which it thus called, <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> Firſt, either becauſe he purchaſed it from the <hi>Amorite with his Sword and</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Hic illius ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, hic currus ſuit, Aecid. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bow:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, or becauſe hee and his Family v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to drinke of it: Thirdly, or becauſe he was poſſeſſour of it: Fourthly, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21975:10"/>he digged it: Fiftly, or yet, becauſe many<note n="l" place="margin">Euentibus vt <hi>1.</hi> Lucta. <hi>2.</hi> Fletibus. <hi>3.</hi> Latebris. <hi>4.</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dereicto. <hi>5.</hi> Statua poſita</note> 
               <hi>changes and chances</hi> happened vnto him at it. As one from his <hi>wreſtling</hi> there: another for his <hi>ſhedding of teares</hi> there: Thirdly, for <hi>hiding himſelfe</hi> there: Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for making a <hi>couenant</hi> there with God: Fiftly and laſtly, for <hi>placing his Image</hi> vpon, or neere vnto it; howſoeuer let vs looke to the <hi>Time,</hi> our fourth occurrent.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, this imperfect pretertenſe, <hi>Erat, Was,</hi> importeth the continuance and perennitie of this <hi>Well,</hi> holding out from <hi>Iacobs</hi> time till our <hi>Sauiours ſitting on it and after.</hi> For this tenſe comprehendeth all the other tenſes, the <hi>preſent,</hi> the <hi>preterper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> and the <hi>futurè,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Th. Aquínas in Ioh. c. <hi>1.</hi> Quod futurum eſt (inquit) non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt actu; Praeſens autem hoc quod ſit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu, non deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fuiſſe; perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum deſignat aliquid extitiſſe, iam eſſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum, etiam deſuiſſe. Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum cerò ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificat aliquid faiſſe, &amp; non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſſe deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum, aut deſuiſſe, ſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buc permancre.</note> as <hi>Thomas Aquinas, Caietan,</hi> and diuers others <hi>Schoole Doctors</hi> Comment vpon that <hi>Verbe</hi> ſubſtantiue <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, in the beginning was the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of which circumſtance of <hi>Time,</hi> wee may obſerue this leſſon, it is better, <hi>Erat, to haue had, and yet haue,</hi> then to heare <hi>Fuit,</hi> or <hi>Erit.</hi> For if the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> had ſaid, <hi>Fons fuit,</hi> that would haue inſinuated the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit was paſt, and is no more, and ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the <hi>Samaritans</hi> miſerie; ſeeing <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt fuiſſe,</hi> as the <hi>Troians, Troes fuimus,</hi> ſpeaking of themſelues, that ſometimes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21975:11"/>they gloriouſly flouriſhed, though after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they were victoriouſly vanquiſhed by the <hi>Grecians:</hi> whereupon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> writes, <hi>Iam ſeges</hi> Eſt <hi>vbi Troia fuit, The ſoyle where</hi> Troy <hi>did ſtand,</hi> Is <hi>now become Corne land.</hi> Nor is <hi>Erit, it will be, or ſhall be hereafter,</hi> ſo good as it was and is ſtill. For although <hi>Erit,</hi> may ſeeme to carrie ſome ſhew of an houering hope of future conſolation, yet is it not halfe ſo comfortable as to enioy a preſent benefit, in regard many things may happen betweene hope and hauing, according to the Greeke<note n="n" place="margin">Multa ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt inter cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſuprema<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> labra,</note> Prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Many things may happen betweene the cup and the lip.</hi> And we ſay in our common ſpeeches, <hi>While the graſſe groweth, the Steed may ſtarue; It is ill hoping for dead mens ſhooes; And one Bird in hand is worth two in the Wood;</hi> a little <hi>in re &amp; eſſe,</hi> is better then much <hi>in ſpe &amp; poſſe:</hi> a ſmal thing in preſent poſſeſſion is more, then a great deale in reuerſion. All to teach vs, that now hauing preſent poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and full fruition of a <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> wee ſhould ſhew our ſelues thankfull to our <hi>Benefactor,</hi> and beware not to miſuſe or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his Benefit or<note n="*" place="margin">Impuris ne quis manibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Lyeo, Hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſontem temeret ſtrepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans hoc mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nda.</note> Conduit.</p>
            <p>So now, Fiftly, to make right <hi>Vſe</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21975:11"/>of <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> (as I referred this effect to that particle, <hi>Now,</hi> in my Text) conſider with me, that a <hi>Well</hi> of <hi>water</hi> muſt needs bee a benefit of a great commoditie and good VSE for them that liue, dwell, or trauell in a dry, hote, ſcorched Countrie, ſuch as was <hi>Sychar.</hi> There the <hi>water</hi> of that <hi>Well</hi> was <hi>neceſſarie, pleaſant,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit vtile dulci. Horat. in Acte Poet.</note> 
               <hi>profitable.</hi> And what matuaile? ſeeing <hi>Water</hi> of it ſelfe is <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> as appeareth by the <hi>Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mologie</hi> of the Latine word<note n="p" place="margin">In Aqua con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare omnia Thal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s dixit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Clem. Alex. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Strom. p. <hi>391.</hi> Ambroſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> Hexam c. <hi>2.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib. <hi>8</hi> de ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dei, c. <hi>2.</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtath. Iliad <hi>0.</hi> p. <hi>1403.</hi> num. <hi>10</hi> Plutar. de Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eitis Philoſoph. Cic de Nat Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Coel. Rhod. lib <hi>17.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lex. ab Alex l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Seruius in Aencid. <hi>11.</hi> Philo Iudaeus lib. <hi>1.</hi> de vita Moſis, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptios aquam eximiè coluiſſe, principium vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſae generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u is eam ce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, confirmauit.</note> AQVA, A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>QVA <hi>omnia naſcuntur:</hi> or as <hi>Feſtus</hi> ſaith, AQVA <hi>juuamur:</hi> or as <hi>Lactantius</hi> AQVA <hi>ſunt omnia,</hi> from which all things proceed. Water is ſo <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> ſaith <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itruuius,</hi> in his eight Booke, intitled <hi>De Aquarum Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus,</hi> that all things are made, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of it, according to <hi>Homers</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtich, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which moued <hi>Pindarus</hi> to beginne to his <hi>Hymnes</hi> thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Water is the beſt thing of all.</hi> What is more <hi>Neceſſary</hi> then <hi>water?</hi> No, not a Friend, for all the Prouerbe. <hi>Who can liue without it?</hi> The firſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt cauſe that moued the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell and mutine with <hi>Moſes,</hi> was for want of <hi>Water;</hi> or elſe for the bitterneſſe of their <hi>Water,</hi> as<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 15.24.</note> 
               <hi>Marah,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Exod 17.7.</note> 
               <hi>Maſſah, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21975:12"/>Meribah can witneſſe.</hi> Reade but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Chapter of <hi>Judeth,</hi> and there you ſhall ſee, how the inhabitants of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> were readie to yeeld vp their <hi>Citie</hi> into the hands of their enemie <hi>Olefernus</hi> for lacke of <hi>water,</hi> if <hi>God</hi> of his goodneſſe had not preuented them in prouiding <hi>water</hi> for them miraculouſly.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſo <hi>pleaſant</hi> is <hi>water,</hi> that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prou. 23.25.</note> likeneth good newes fetcht out of a farre Country vnto coole waters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting a thirſtie ſoule. One and the ſame word, in the ſacred <hi>Fountaine-Tongue</hi> is ſet for an <hi>Eye,</hi> and for a <hi>Well,</hi> or <hi>Fountaine;</hi> and euen (you ſee) the <hi>Eye</hi> is of a watery con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, to teach vs not vnfitly, that as the <hi>Eyes</hi> are neceſſarie and beautifull ſprings to grace the<note n="t" place="margin">Aequem Greci <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> nomine appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti, cum &amp; nos à perfecta abſoluta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia, Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, Plin. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Little World</hi> of our bodies; ſo <hi>Fountaines</hi> of water are as <hi>Eyes</hi> to beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and ſolace the <hi>Greater World,</hi> of the <hi>Earth.</hi> Therefore the Lord to encourage his people in the Wilderneſſe promiſed to bring them vnto a good land, <hi>A land of Brookes of Waters of Fountaines, Wels and Depths that ſpring out of the Vallayes and</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Deut. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Water is moſt<note n="x" place="margin">D. Hierom in Epiſt. ad Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de Schola Rhetorum A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarum laudes eleganter praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat.</note> 
               <hi>profitable,</hi> to all things, as appeareth in that <hi>God</hi> made
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21975:12"/>good <hi>vſe</hi> of it from the beginning of the world. In the Creation,<note n="y" place="margin">Gon. 1.</note> 
               <hi>the Spirit of God moued vpon the face of the waters:</hi> and God ſaid, <hi>Let there be a firmament in the midſt of waters:</hi> and let <hi>diuide the waters from the waters:</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 6.7.8.</note> Hee drew the firſt liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of <hi>water:</hi> and hee watered the earth with <hi>water</hi> to make Man: by <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hee deſtroyed the world: hee drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Aegyptian</hi> armie by <hi>water,</hi> and freed the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> from their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by <hi>water.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh 2.</note> IESVS the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> turned <hi>water</hi> into <hi>wine.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Math. 3.</note> Hee was <hi>baptized</hi> by <hi>water:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mare. 6.</note> He walked vpon the <hi>waters</hi> and commanded them: and<note n="e" place="margin">Joh. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus being wearied with his</hi> ſecond <hi>iourney</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Galile <hi>ſate thus on Iacobs Well,</hi> to reſt and refreſh himſelfe and others: yea euen<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 46.4.</note> 
               <hi>To make glad the Citie of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Jacobs Well was there<note n="g" place="margin">Ingredior ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cros auſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludere Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. <hi>Virg. Geor.</hi> 2.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iam incipiunt Myſteria</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Auguſtin. tract. <hi>15.</hi> in Ioh.</note>: Now to draw deeper then hitherto, and to fetch out of this <hi>Well</hi> other then vulgar and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie <hi>Water,</hi> conſider <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe is <hi>Iacob</hi> and his <hi>Well.</hi> For hee is <hi>Fons Vitae,</hi> THE FOVNTAINE OF LIFE<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 36.9. Iſa. 12.3.</note>, and as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, 12.3. <hi>Out of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21975:13"/>this Well,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 12.3.</note> haurietis aquas in gaudio Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatoris, <hi>with ioy ſhall yee draw water of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> By <hi>Water,</hi> is vnderſtood <hi>Learning, Wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> in generall, as <hi>S. Origen, Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, interpret this <hi>Text</hi> of the <hi>Euangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</hi> So <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake to the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> Deuteronomie 32.2. <hi>My doctrine ſhall droppe as the raine, my ſpeach ſhall diſtill as the deaw. Moſes</hi> himſelfe is thought to haue had his name from his <hi>Learning,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then from that hee was drawen and dragged out of the Flags, and<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Moyſes</hi> quaſi ex Aqua emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: <hi>Moy</hi> enim Aquam Aegyptij vocant. Clem. Alex. l. <hi>2.</hi> Strom. p <hi>369.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oachim à pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſione, Melchi verò in coelis, vt dicunt Myſtae.</note> 
               <hi>Water.</hi> For <hi>Moſes</hi> was <hi>learned in all the doctrine of the Aegyptians:</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> themſelues figured their myſtical doctrine vnder an Hierogliphicke of a rainy and ouercloudy heauen.</p>
            <p>Hence the fabulous <hi>Poets</hi> imputed all their enthuſiaſmes, or ſo daine inſpirations, vnto certaine <hi>Wells</hi> and <hi>Fountaines</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Nec Fonte la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra prolui Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellino, ſic vt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pente Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direm. Perſ. in Prolog. Vnde Pater ſitiens Eunius ante bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit. Propert. cleg. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> &amp; multi alii.</note>. So the <hi>Athenian</hi> and <hi>Roman Orators</hi> compared their <hi>Eloquence</hi> to <hi>ſtreames</hi> of <hi>water,</hi> calling it, <hi>flumen orationis, vbertatem dicendi;</hi> diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, <hi>in grandem alueum, modicum, &amp; exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Likewiſe the ancient <hi>Philoſophers</hi> were named commonly <hi>Fontes Philoſophiae, Wels of Learning;</hi> as namely in <hi>Morall Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21975:13"/>Water</hi> is taken for the foure <hi>Cardinall Vertues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now aboue all other <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> out of this <hi>Well,</hi> yee ſhall draw the <hi>doctrine</hi> of <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> briefly comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the <hi>Holy Bible,</hi> more ſummarily contained in the name of IESVS, which is the <hi>ſacred Fountaine</hi> of all <hi>Learning.</hi> For <hi>in him are</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Coloſ. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>hid all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge:</hi> and as <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaid,<note n="h" place="margin">Ecclus. 24.31.</note> 
               <hi>I will water aboundantly my Garden-bed; and loe, my Brooke became a Riuer, and my Riuer became a Sea.</hi> And true, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the little <hi>Well,</hi> that became<note n="*" place="margin">Flumina mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fluunt paruis de Fontibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</note> a <hi>Riuer,</hi> and ouerflowed with great waters: Hee is euen <hi>Ezechiels Riuer,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ezech. 47.</note> which iſſued from vnder the threſhold of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, at firſt it did ariſe but to the ancles, then to the knees, afterwards to the loines, and at laſt became a Riuer that ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Surely this made the <hi>Woman of Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> ſay,<note n="k" place="margin">Iohn 4.</note> 
               <hi>Puteus eſt profundus, The Well is deepe,</hi> and ſo ſoone as ſhee had taſted of the <hi>water</hi> of it, <hi>left her water-pot, and went her way into the Citie, and ſaid to the men of Sychar, Come, ſee a man, which told mee all things that euer I did: is not this the Christ?</hi> And ſhee ſaid to <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Sir, giue
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21975:14"/>me this water, that I thirſt not, neither come hither to draw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ho</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſai. 55.1.</note> then, <hi>euery one that thirſteth, come yee to theſe waters, and he that hath no money: come yee, buy and eate, yea come, buy wine and milke without money, and without price! Come,</hi> this is <hi>Chriſts</hi> call,<note n="m" place="margin">Nulli praclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa gratia eſt, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nil us patet, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos admittit, omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s inuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ingenu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinos, ſernos, Reges, &amp; exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. Non eligit domum nec cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, nudo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine contenta eſt. Senec. de Ben. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> generally inuiting all perſons of what age, ranke, degree, eſtate, or ſexe ſoeuer in time of Grace, as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly onely to the Elect in day of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>Come,</hi> ſaith hee, meaning your <hi>ſelues,</hi> and that you <hi>ſend not; To mee,</hi> that is, not to <hi>any other,</hi> neither to <hi>Angels,</hi> or to <hi>Saints,</hi> but onely to <hi>Him,</hi> the <hi>Fountaine of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe many haue forſaken this <hi>Fountaine of liuing waters,</hi> and digged to themſelues<note n="n" place="margin">Ier. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Ciſternes</hi> which hold no <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of ſaluation, it ſhall not be amiſſe to diſcouer vnto you theſe foule <hi>Ciſternes,</hi> or muddy <hi>Wells,</hi> before I giue you a taſte of this wholſome <hi>water</hi> of <hi>Iacobs Well</hi> in a ſpirituall ſenſe. Theſe <hi>Ciſternes</hi> are called in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the<note n="o" place="margin">2. Rec. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Samaritans Well,</hi> or otherwiſe,<note n="p" place="margin">Nehem. 2. Iude, 5. Exod. 15. Ierem. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Fons Draconis, Fons Amaritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis, Fons Sanguinis, Fons Lachrymarum,</hi> which are of a farre contrarie nature and different reliſh to that <hi>water,</hi> of this <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21975:14"/>Fountaine.</hi> For they were ſtopped by the <hi>Prophet Ezechiel,</hi> when <hi>Sannacharib</hi> came to beſiege the <hi>Citie</hi> of<note n="q" place="margin">2. Paralip. 32. &amp; 4. Reg 18.</note> 
               <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> I meane theſe muddy <hi>Wells</hi> are the <hi>Roman dirty Ciſternes</hi> which are ſtopped and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp with their owne <hi>ſelfe-merits, Saint merits, Supererogations, Satisfactions,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Vide Taxam. Camerae Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae &amp; Claud. Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>encaeum. in Titum.</note> 
               <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, Indulgences,</hi> and ſuch traſh and trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> I ſay, (to ſpeake more plainly) endeauour what in them lieth to ſlander the <hi>pure Fountaine of Gods ſacred Scriptures,</hi> with <hi>imperfections</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Voié l'Inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficience, &amp; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection de l'Eſcriture Saincte de Sieur de Perron, Eueſque d'Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reux. contre Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenus l'an <hi>1598.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Bellarm. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</note>; to ſtoppe them vp with <hi>Traditions, Gloſſes, frothie Legends,</hi> and <hi>Lying fictions,</hi> of <hi>Miracles.</hi> They haue puddled and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with <hi>Salt, Oyle,</hi> and <hi>Spittle,</hi> the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall water</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> being the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> of our <hi>New-birth.</hi> So haue they ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed the <hi>Sacramentall Fountaine</hi> of <hi>Chriſts bodie and bloud,</hi> with a maſſe of <hi>Idolatries, Adorations, Eleuations, Genuflexions,</hi> and ſuch mimicke trickes, driuing the <hi>Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>people</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pigh. Hierar. Eccleſ l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Coſter. Enchirid. c. <hi>1.</hi> Lindan. Panop. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> &amp;c. Detorquentes (inquit) quò volunt ſacra Scripta.</note> as vncleane beaſts, from the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſtreame</hi> of his precious <hi>Bloud</hi> in the <hi>Cup.</hi> To be briefe, What <hi>ſacred Order,</hi> or <hi>Ordinance</hi> haue they not ſtained, or defiled more or leſſe, with the filth and dung of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21975:15"/>their owne idle <hi>Inuentions,</hi> and blind <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Superſtitio fuſa per gentes oppreſſit omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ferè animos, atque hominum imbecillitatem occupauit Cic. de Diuinat. <hi>2.</hi> Coeca ſuperſtitio ſeſe in caligine condens obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vera inuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, quo falſa reponit.</note>?</p>
            <p>To diſcerne then the one <hi>Well</hi> from the <hi>other;</hi> that of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> from this of <hi>Jacobs Well,</hi> obſerue theſe fiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the <hi>Water</hi> drawen out of <hi>Jacobs Well,</hi> ſubiect to our fiue externall ſenſes. One is the <hi>cleareneſſe</hi> of it, to the <hi>Eye:</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is the <hi>harmonious Sound</hi> of it to the <hi>Eare:</hi> the third is the <hi>ſweet Smell</hi> of it, to the <hi>Noſe:</hi> the fourth is the <hi>pleaſant Taſte,</hi> to the <hi>Palate:</hi> the fift and laſt is the <hi>Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> or <hi>feeling,</hi> to our<note n="y" place="margin">Therein our Fingers feele, our Noſtrils ſmell, our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats taſte his vertues that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. It ſhewes to your Eies, talkes to your Eares, &amp;c. Du Bartas in his firſt weekes worke.</note> 
               <hi>Fingers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the <hi>Clearneſſe</hi> of it, it is certaine <hi>Nunquam floriferis Fons purior,</hi> the criſtall was neuer clearer, fairer, and finer to the ſight then it. For the words of the Lord,<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> 
               <hi>are pure as ſiluer tryed and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied ſeuen times in a Fornace.</hi> And as it is ſaid in the Reuelation<note n="a" place="margin">Reuel. 22.</note>; <hi>Hee ſhewed me a pure riuer of Water of life, cleare as criſtall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out of the Throne of God.</hi> Nay this <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of this <hi>Well</hi> is ſo cleare, pure, neate, and tranſparent, that it will not admit mixture with any other <hi>water;</hi> no more then the quiet, calme, and gentle <hi>Lake of Geneua</hi> will haue acquaintance, with the raging, rouing, and roring <hi>Riuer of Roane,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21975:15"/>which runneth through the <hi>Lake:</hi> nor no better will it ſort, and agree with other <hi>Waters</hi> then the freſh <hi>Riuer</hi> of <hi>Arethuſa</hi> can ſort with the ſalt <hi>Sycilian</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Per ſalſa flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem aequora, dulcorem inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumen ſeruare, nec vllam illis immiſceri labem Aen. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon heere it may be doubted, or demanded, whether wee may vſe <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Learning, Arts,</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> in our <hi>Sermons</hi> and diuine <hi>Diſcourſes?</hi> whereunto I anſwere that in citing of <hi>humane writs</hi> for illuſtrating points of <hi>Diuinitie,</hi> it is not ſo common, as commendable, if it be done without vanitie and oſtentation, making choice of the beſt Authours for better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Text, and more cleere declaration of the truth. <hi>Sit illa Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix caeterae illi Mediaſtinae;</hi> ſo being, <hi>Dame Sara ſits in the Chaire of State, Agar and her Handmaids may attend and ſerue her.</hi> This was the iudgement of <hi>Origen in his ſeuenth Homily vpon the tenth Chapter of Leuitious,</hi> ſaying,<note n="y" place="margin">Quaecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hene &amp; ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabiliter dicta inucnimus apud inimicos noſtros, oportet nos mun dare &amp; reſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care omne quod emortuum &amp; inane eſt, hoc enim ſunt omnes capilli capitis, &amp; vngulae mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris ex inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum ſpolijs aſſumptae, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendeco citato.</note> 
               <hi>When any of Iſrael tooke a maide in battaile, he firſt pared her nayles, and ſhaued her head, before he married her;</hi> ſo we muſt pare away in <hi>humane Learning</hi> all things noxius before wee captiue it to the vſe of <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> And with him agreeth <hi>Saint Auguſtine in his ſecond Booke of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, Chap.</hi> 40. <hi>VVe</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Philoſophi ſi quae vera &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei noſtrae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoda dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, non ſolum formidanda non ſunt, ſed ab iis etiam tanquam ab iniuſtis poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus in vſum noſtrum ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicanda. Aug. de doct. Chriſt. l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>rob the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21975:16"/>of their jewels, when we conuert Arts and Sciences to the vſe of Theologie.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Clem. Alex. quam multus eſt de hac re, l. <hi>1.</hi> Strom. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clement of Alexandria, Saint Baſil the Great, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Nizanzen, Tertullian, Arnobius,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Lactantius, l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> eas opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè conciliat multis rationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> 
               <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius, Saint Hierome,</hi> and diuers others of the <hi>Fathers</hi> illuſtrate their doctrine with authorities of <hi>Heathen Authors</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Sidon. Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</note> 
               <hi>vt neſcias quid in eis primum mirari debeas, eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem populi, vel ſcientiam Scripturarum. Art thou greater then, then our Father Iacob,</hi> and the <hi>Fathers, which gaue vs the VVell, and dranke thereof himſelfe, his children, and his cattell. Chriſt</hi> himſelfe reaſoned many times from things earthly, to things hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly,<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> and <hi>Saint Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Galathians</hi> 3.6. argueth the caſe from the poſitions of <hi>Lawyers</hi> and <hi>Politicians:</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly he citeth three ſeuerall ſentences out of <hi>prophane Poets,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Aratus.</note> 
               <hi>Acts</hi> 17.18.<note n="b" place="margin">Menander.</note> 1. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</hi> 15.33.<note n="c" place="margin">Epimenides.</note> 
               <hi>Titus</hi> 1.22. Yea hee became a <hi>Iew,</hi> that hee might gaine the <hi>Jewes, &amp;c. and ſo made all things to all men, that he might by all meanes ſaue ſome.</hi> In my opinion to this point, the Spider is neuer the more commendable becauſe hee weaueth his web out of his owne bowels, neither is the Bee deſpiſed, becauſe ſhe gathereth her honey out of diuers flowers.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21975:16"/>
Conſider againe the <hi>colour</hi> of our <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Aqua in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſas plerum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſe mutat, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies aut inter arenas ſlaua, aut inter caules ſpumea, aut inter nemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora viridan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior, aut inter florenta diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, aut inter lilia fulgentior, aut inter roſeta rutilantior, aut in gramine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidior, aut in Palude turbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior, aut in Fonte prospica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cior, aut in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri obſcurior, <hi>Ambroſ.</hi>
               </note> which although in the <hi>Well or Spring,</hi> it is alwayes <hi>vniforme</hi> and of the <hi>ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour alike,</hi> yet in the courſe and running of it, there is nothing more variable and changeable then it, according to its Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects. As on the ſands it is of golden co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; amongſt the rockes and ſtones it is froathy; along Medowes it is greene; in running through Gardens, amongſt Flowers it is like the Rainbow; ſo in the <hi>Word of God, there are diuerſities of gifts but the ſame Spirit; diuerſities of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but the ſame Lord; diuerſities of opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but God is the ſame who worketh all in all,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.</p>
            <p>There were diuerſities of gifts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as boldneſſe in <hi>Peter;</hi> profoundneſſe in <hi>Paul;</hi> loftineſſe in <hi>Iohn,</hi> compared to an <hi>Eagle;</hi> vehemencie both in <hi>him,</hi> and his brother <hi>Iames,</hi> ſirnamed the <hi>Sonnes of Thunder;</hi> ſeruencie of ſpirit in <hi>Simon the Zealous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diuerſities of gifts amongſt the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> whereof ſome conſtrued the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture litterally,</hi> as <hi>Hierome;</hi> others, <hi>Allegori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally,</hi> as <hi>Origen;</hi> others, <hi>morally,</hi> as <hi>Gregorie the great;</hi> others <hi>Rathetically,</hi> as <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21975:17"/>others <hi>dogmatically,</hi> as<note n="g" place="margin">Sextu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis Biblioth. Patrium lib. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>187.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> all of them (as worthy<note n="h" place="margin">Enar. ſymbol. Nicene. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>393.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Melancthon</hi> is bold to deliuer) in the mayne <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Apoſtolically.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So were there diuerſities of gifts among our moderne Writers, as <hi>Luther</hi> wrote on the walls of his Chamber with Chalke:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">In colloquio de Eraſmo.</note>Res &amp; verba <hi>Philippus,</hi> res ſine verbis <hi>Lutherus.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erba ſine re <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> nec res, nec verba <hi>Carolaſtadius.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Who more <hi>compendious</hi> then <hi>Caluine?</hi> more <hi>eloquent</hi> then <hi>Beza?</hi> more <hi>iudicious</hi> then <hi>Martyr?</hi> more <hi>copious</hi> then <hi>Zanchie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, there are diuerſities of gifts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thoſe of this <hi>Reuerend Society,</hi> which I reſemble to the twelue <hi>Fountaines at</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 15.27.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim;</hi> or rather, to <hi>Iacob</hi> and his <hi>twelue Sons</hi> the<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 46.27</note> 
               <hi>Patriarchs;</hi> or more fitly for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to <hi>Ieſus</hi> with his <hi>twelue Apoſtles;</hi> mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Master Deane</hi> and the <hi>twelue</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Bis ſex coele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, medio Ioue, ſedibus altis, Auguſta graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſedent.</note> 
               <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends;</hi> whom I commend thus, according to the graces and gifts of God beſtowed vpon them ſeuerally and<note n="n" place="margin">In eloquendo eſt aliqua diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit as: denſior ille hic copioſior i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le concludit ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiùs, hic latiùs: pugnat ille ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumine ſemper, hic frequenter &amp; pond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re; illi nihil detrabi poteſt, huic nihil adiici, curae plus in illo, in hoc naturae, Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. lib. <hi>10.6.1.</hi>
               </note> diuerſly, in <hi>one conſent of faith:</hi> as <hi>ſweetneſſe in Socrates; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie in Lyſias; ſharpneſſe in Hyperides; ſhril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Aeſchines; powerfulneſſe in Demoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenes; grauitie in Aphrican; ſmoothneſſe in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21975:17"/>Loelius; copiouſneſſe in Carbo; learning in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laemon; the ſtately ſtile of Agraecius; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodicall diſcourſe of Alcimus; the mincing-like of Adelphius,</hi> and the <hi>flowing tongue of your Learned Lecturer,</hi> whom I may iuſtly name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, <hi>flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioſum,</hi> ſuch is the volubility of his ſpeech, and other diuers gifts.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe there are diuerſities of gifts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>ſixe Preachers of this Church,</hi> whom I name vnder theſe Titles of ſixe other old <hi>Orators;</hi> as <hi>adſtrictior Caluus; nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meroſior Aſinius; ſplendidior Caeſar; amatior Coelius; grauior Brutus; plenior Tullius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And (with permiſſion) there are diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of gifts amongſt vs<note n="o" place="margin">Non omnia poſſumus omnes Nihil eſt ab omni parte bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Hor. lib. <hi>2.</hi> carm Od. <hi>16.</hi> ex Pindaro Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide, Theog.</note> 
               <hi>ordinarie and rurall Miniſters,</hi> who come hither now and then vpon intreatie; <hi>Alij ſenſu ampli, ſed non ore; alij ſenſu inopes, ſed ore torrentes; alij ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſenſu ampli, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ore; alij ſenſu ampli &amp; ore. Some</hi> haue bad vtterance, but a good conceit; <hi>others</hi> an excellent vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but a meane wit; <hi>ſome</hi> neither; and <hi>ſome</hi> both. <hi>One</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">p</hi> ſurpaſſeth in expounding the words; <hi>another</hi> is excellent in deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the matter; <hi>a third</hi> happy for caſes of conſcience; <hi>a fourth</hi> exquiſite in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Schoole-doubts. In a word, <hi>ſome</hi> be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21975:18"/>iudicious to enforme the vnderſtanding, <hi>others</hi> powerfull to reforme the will and affections. <hi>All theſe diuers gifts are from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, comming downe from one and the ſame Fountaine with whom is no variableneſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhadow of turning. Iames Chapter.</hi> 1. <hi>Ver.</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Turne and hearken to the <hi>purling noyſe</hi> of this our <hi>Water,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ebullit ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus me us ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum bonum, <hi>Pſal. 46.</hi>
               </note> boyling and bubling vp at the <hi>Springs head.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Fontibus at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> antris, gaudens &amp; montibus, Echo! Frangit inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletas, iterato murmure voces.</note> Heare how the <hi>water</hi> guſheth, floweth, and ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth out on euery ſide, how the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> 
               <hi>ſound of Gods word is gone out into all Lands.</hi> This ſound was propheſied by <hi>King Dauid,</hi> commanded by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> practiſed by his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and euer to bee performed by their<note n="t" place="margin">Acts 2.46.</note> 
               <hi>Succeſſors.</hi> We ſhould all <hi>pray, prayſe</hi> and <hi>preach</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> with one accord. And in very deed,<note n="u" place="margin">Patriarcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vinculum, Prophetarum vehiculum, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium, Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſolatium, Author lib. ad fratres in here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſerm. de pace</note> 
               <hi>This is the life of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, the bond of the Patriarchs, the Chariot of the Prophets, the refuge of the Apoſtles, the ſolace of Martyrs, a ſigne and token of the Church Militant heere on earth, and an holy exerciſe of the Church Triumphant aboue in Heauen.</hi> Without which eloquence is but vaine, Propheſie is vnperfect, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is nothing, Faith is dead, the workes of mercie are reiected, Martyrdome it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21975:18"/>ſelfe is not accepted, all other gifts and graces of the ſpirit are but as a <hi>ſounding braſſe and tinkling Cymball.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The ſmell of Iacob is as the ſmell of a field, which the Lord hath</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gen 27.27.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed:</hi> and the <hi>Water of his Well</hi> excelleth all other <hi>Waters</hi> in ſent whatſoeuer, whether they are naturally ſweet,<note place="margin">Ecclus 39.13.</note> or by art and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. For<note n="y" place="margin">Aliter olet flos vuae, aliter flos oliuae, aliter flos roſae, aliter flos lilii, aliter flos violae, aliter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolet ſpica &amp;c. Gregor. homil. <hi>5.</hi> in Ezechiel.</note> 
               <hi>although the Roſe hath its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſweet ſmell by it ſelfe; the Lilly by it ſelfe; the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolet, the Pinke, the Gilly-flower,</hi> and ſo the reſt by themſelues, yet are they not put together for ſweet ſent comparable to the <hi>water</hi> of this <hi>Well.</hi> Nor was that <hi>Well</hi> neere to <hi>Miſſenum,</hi> which<note n="z" place="margin">Cardanus de Subtilitate.</note> 
               <hi>Cardanus</hi> writes, ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo ſweet of <hi>Cizinum,</hi> as if it had beene compounded of the root of <hi>Iris, of Saffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, and of Myrrhe;</hi> nor was that moſt fragrant and odoriferous <hi>Fountaine of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burra in Meſopotamia,</hi> ſo ſweete and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to the ſmell, as <hi>Iacobs Well.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the fooliſh Antiquitie imagined their fabulous <hi>Goddeſſe</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Home <hi>Iuno</hi> fer tur terris magis omnibus vnam, Poſtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitam coluiſſe <hi>Samo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iuno</hi> ſate ofttimes on that <hi>Well,</hi> and therefore cauſed it ſmell ſo ſweetly; yet it is certaine, our true <hi>God</hi> IESVS ſate <hi>thus</hi> on <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> and ſo made it ſmell farre ſweeter.<note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>And thankes bee vnto God, which alwayes maketh
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21975:19"/>manifeſt the ſauour of his knowledge by vs in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place: for we are vnto God a ſweet ſauour of Christ, in them that are ſaued, and in them that periſh. To the one wee are the ſauour of death vnto death, and to the other the ſauour of life vnto life; and who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note> 
               <hi>Taſte alſo how good is the Lord;</hi> how this <hi>water</hi> exceedeth all other <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> in <hi>taſte</hi> to the palate; euen the <hi>waters of</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Coaspi &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leui fluuiorum fic adeò ſuaues aquae fuiſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunturr vt ex cis Reges biberent vnde &amp; dici poſſent fluuii Regum, ab illo vſu: qua de re Aelianus var. biſt. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>40.</hi> Herodot. Plin. lib. <hi>31.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coaspes,</hi> and <hi>Euleus</hi> which the <hi>Perſians</hi> eſteemed ſo much. For allthough the <hi>waters</hi> of theſe two <hi>Riuers</hi> prolonged the liues of the <hi>Kings of Perſia,</hi> yet they made them not to liue for euer; but whoſoeuer drinketh of our <hi>water,</hi> it ſhall be in him <hi>a Well of water ſpringing vp into euerlaſting life.</hi> So whoſoeuer drinketh of any other <hi>water,</hi> thirſteth againe,<note n="e" place="margin">Rupert. in <hi>4.</hi> Ioh.</note> and the oftner he drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the more is hee dry; But whoſoeuer drinketh oc this <hi>water</hi> ſhall neuer thirſt. What ſay I this <hi>water</hi> is better in <hi>taſte</hi> then all other <hi>waters,</hi> when it is more pleaſant to the palate, and more profitable to the heart then<note n="f" place="margin">Clitorio qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſitim de Fonte leuaret Vina fugit, gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> meris ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemius vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>Wine,</hi> euen then that <hi>wine</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; <hi>Monembraticum Cretenſe,</hi> or that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inum germinans</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Scalig. exerc. <hi>99.</hi> pag. <hi>339.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>virgines,</hi> which were in ſo great account amongſt the Ancients? for the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21975:19"/>firſt cup of <hi>wine</hi> is <hi>pleaſure,</hi> the ſecond cup is <hi>loſſe of ſenſes,</hi> and the third of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance;</hi> or as <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 25.</note> ſaith, <hi>At the last it biteth like a Serpent, and ſtingeth like an Adder, or a Cockatrice</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Baſiliſcum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt ſuo aspectu corrump<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſuos ſpectatoros., Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. in c. <hi>3.</hi> in Eſa. p <hi>685.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ ſerm. <hi>10.</hi> in Pſ. <hi>118.</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can lib. <hi>9</hi> Plin. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> where our <hi>water</hi> is that <hi>Nectar</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> which <hi>Homer</hi> ſaid the <hi>Heathen Gods</hi> did drinke; or it may be called the <hi>Nepenthes</hi> of alluring <hi>Helena,</hi> which bewitched all diſpleaſure, and it made men forget their greateſt troubles and vexations, as was fained of the Riuer<note n="k" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g. Aen <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lethe. Let vs giue this water then to him that is readie to periſh, and to thoſe that bee of heauie</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Prou. 31.6.</note> 
               <hi>hearts.</hi> for this <hi>water</hi> is more cordiall then any diſtilled hote <hi>water</hi> ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; nay, it is more healthfull, light, and of eaſie digeſtion in the ſtomacke, ſeeing it is a <hi>Well of water ſpringing vp into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> And ſeeing the nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of common and ordinarie <hi>water</hi> is, to aſcend againe ſo high, as from whence it diſcended at<note n="m" place="margin">Repetunt proprios quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recurſus, reditu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſuo ſingula gaudent, Boet. <hi>3</hi> proſ. <hi>2.</hi> de conſol.</note> firſt, it is no maruell our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſaid, <hi>I came forth from the Father, and am come into the world: againe, I leaue the</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iohn 16.28.</note> 
               <hi>world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, this is likewiſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and propertie of good <hi>water</hi> onely to taſte of <hi>water,</hi> and to haue no other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21975:20"/>relliſh in the mouth;<note n="y" place="margin">Sicut aquae nullus ineſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c ſuccus, vel ſapor, vel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, teſte Plinio, lib. <hi>15.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi> ita aquae idiuinae gratiae nullus admiſceri debet ſapor vel odor terrae, ſed Coeli ac Dei ipſius vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de venit. Amor Dei ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aliud quaerit praeter Deum, cuncta ſpernit, cuncta deſpicit, omnia ſibi vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcunt; quia ei ſolus Chriſtus dulceſcit. Ber. ſerm. <hi>9.</hi> in Caena Domini.</note> ſo this <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Iacobs Well</hi> taſtes onely of <hi>God,</hi> and of no other thing, not of the <hi>World,</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> or of the <hi>Deuill.</hi> z It is true, ſome <hi>water</hi> is brackiſh, and taſtes of Salt, ſome of Steele, or of Iron, ſome of ſome minerall or of other; but the <hi>water</hi> of <hi>Iacobs Well</hi> is moſt ſweet, and taſtes onely of <hi>Honie,</hi> as was <hi>prophecied, Pſalme,</hi> 81.16. <hi>And with Honie out of the Rocke, ſhould I haue ſatisfied thee. Brethren I would not that yee ſhould be ignorant, how that all our Fathers did drinke of that ſpirituall Rocke, and that Rocke was Chriſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.1.</p>
            <p>Fiftly and finally, the <hi>Feeling</hi> of this <hi>Water</hi> is not only ſenſible to the <hi>fiue ſenſes,</hi> without, but alſo it is common to the <hi>common ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Phantaſie</hi> within<note n="a" place="margin">Nihil in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu quod non ſuerit prius in ſenſu. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotel. Scalig. ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcit. <hi>18</hi> &amp; <hi>307.</hi> a duerſus Cardanum.</note>. For this <hi>Well</hi> is the <hi>Poole of Betheſda, hauing fiue Porches,</hi> by which whoſoeuer goeth into it with Faith, hee ſhall be cured from all diſeaſes, ſickneſſes, ſorrowes, and ſores ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer<note n="b" place="margin">Omnia Ieſus Chriſtus eſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis ſi volumus: curari deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas? medicus eſt; ſchribus aeſtuas? ſons eſt; grauaris iniquitate? iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la eſt; auxilio indiges? virtus eſt; mortem ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes? vita eſt, &amp;c. Ambroſ. lib. de virginit.</note>. IESVS is the <hi>Well,</hi> and <hi>Hee</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of the <hi>fiue letters</hi> in his <hi>Name,</hi> and ſo many <hi>wounds</hi> on <hi>his precious Bodie,</hi> may be iuſtly called ПEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAФIAON, or the <hi>Name of fiue letters,</hi> bearing this word YГEIA in <hi>Greeke; Salus</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21975:20"/>in <hi>Latine; Salue</hi> in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> as that ПEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TATION, which in former times, was my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly reuealed vnto <hi>King Antiochus,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Sauiour,</hi> for the ſauing and deliuering the bodies of his<note n="b" place="margin">Reuclin. lib. 3. de Caba!. Euſeb. in vita Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tini lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> people; whereas IESVS ſaueth both the <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>ſoules</hi> of his people; <hi>His owne,</hi> and of <hi>others; once,</hi> and <hi>for euer;</hi> and therefore moſt worthily to be called our <hi>Sauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus hauing diſcouered <hi>Iacobs well</hi> plainly enough, ſo that we can diſtinguiſh it from that foule <hi>Well</hi> of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> wee muſt conſider now, one of the firſt, chiefe, and neceſſarie meanes to ſaue vs, is by <hi>waſhing</hi> with the <hi>water</hi> of it.<note n="c" place="margin">O Aqua quae Chriſti Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum eſſc meruiſti, quae lauas omnia, nec lauar is. Tu in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis prima, tu comples perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta myſteria. Ambroſ. in Luc. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſt himſelfe</hi> aſſureth vs this in a double aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueration thus;<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Verily, verily, except a man be borne of Water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> Where <hi>Water</hi> is an outward neceſſarie meane to our Regeneration<note n="e" place="margin">Com. Catechiſt</note>, ſo the <hi>Spirit</hi> is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward cauſe, and therefore both be ioyned in our <hi>Baptiſme.</hi> For<note n="f" place="margin">Anglicana confeſſ. artic. <hi>27.</hi> &amp; art. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baptiſme is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſigne of profeſsion, and marke of difference, whereby Chriſtian men are diſcerned from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be not chriſtned: but it is a ſigne of Regeneration, whereby as by an inſtrument they that receiue Baptiſme rightly, are grafted into
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21975:21"/>the Church.</hi> And as<note n="a" place="margin">Serm. <hi>14.</hi> de Paſſion. Dom. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Christ:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 5.30.</note> fleſh as it were of <hi>Chriſts</hi> fleſh, and bone of <hi>his</hi> bone: the <hi>Spirit</hi> in this our <hi>New birth</hi> is in ſtead of a <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Water</hi> in<note n="c" place="margin">Maldonat. in locum.</note> ſtead of a <hi>Mother.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this ſenſe the Scripture tearmes <hi>Baptiſme a</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Tit. 3 5.</note> 
               <hi>Bath of Regeneration,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 26.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>God</hi> cleanſeth his <hi>Church,</hi> vnto<note n="f" place="margin">Act 3.38.</note> remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes: and hence may wee ſay and ſing of <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> as<note n="g" place="margin">Paulinus ep. <hi>12.</hi> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euerum.</note> 
               <hi>Paulinus</hi> wrote of the <hi>Fountaine</hi> of his <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Hic reparandarum generator fons anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</l>
               <l>Viuum diuino flamine flumen agit:</l>
               <l>Sanctus in hunc coelo, deſcendit Spiritus amnem</l>
               <l>Coeleſti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſacras igne maritat aquas.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hence<note n="h" place="margin">Non li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit Iſraelitis, niſi lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, purgatis, &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeparatis, manna veſci, &amp;c. Quid igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hinc dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus? Niſi quod oportebat fidei Baptiſma lauari omni victure, omni Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca doctrina, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndos pureſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> animos noſtros: ſacere: ita vt omnimo alieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geni mores &amp; Algyptiaca cita, vitiorum ſcil. omnium turba nos deſerat, &amp; demum depura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, deſaecate<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimo coeleſtem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ibum eſſe acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendum. Haec omnia Nyſſenus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vita Moyſis.</note> moreouer we may eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, there was neuer any <hi>Sect</hi> or <hi>Religion, true</hi> or <hi>falſe, Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Ethnicke,</hi> in which they did not vſe to <hi>waſh,</hi> before euer they entred into their <hi>Congregation.</hi> As in the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> it was written vpon the doore of <hi>Diana's Temple,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: in the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> it was commanded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine of death, that none ſhould come into the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> before they waſhed; and for this purpoſe, the <hi>Lauer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21975:21"/>(made of womens Looking glaſſes)</hi> was ſet at the doore of the <hi>Tabernacle. Exod.</hi> 30.20. and the <hi>Iewes</hi> at this day <hi>waſh</hi> before euer they enter into their <hi>Synagogues.</hi> So you ſee in all <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> the <hi>Font</hi> is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the great doore and firſt entrie, as commonly in euery <hi>Cathedrall Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> (as here) there is a <hi>Conduit,</hi> ſignifying we muſt all be <hi>waſhed</hi> by the <hi>water of Baptiſme.</hi> The <hi>Turkes</hi> likewiſe <hi>waſh</hi> before they goe into their <hi>Moſquees:</hi> and the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Gentiles waſhed,</hi> before euer they could be admitted vnto their ſuperſtitious <hi>Sacrifices</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Macrob. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. Aenei <hi>6.</hi> Ouid. Faſt <hi>5.</hi> Perſius Satyr. <hi>2.</hi> Ex principe peë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta declarat. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin l. <hi>21.</hi> de Cuit. Dei, c. <hi>13.</hi> Seruius praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea hoc explicat. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de hac re vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendus Clem. Alexand. l. <hi>7.</hi> Stromat.</note>. After whoſe example, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, thoſe of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> ſprinkle themſelues with <hi>Holy-water,</hi> at their firſt comming into their <hi>Synagogues</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ter ſocios pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra circumfluit vn la, Spargens rore leui. &amp;c. Virg. Beller. tom. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>2.</hi> De Aqua benedicta. &amp;c.</note>. Seeing then, <hi>waſhing</hi> hath euer beene in vſe, in all ages, among all nations and people what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, why ſhould wee not <hi>waſh</hi> before all our ſpirituall exerciſes, and diuine acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? eſpecially in regard, IESVS <hi>at this time hath ſet open a Fountaine for Judah, and Hieruſalem to waſh in?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet before wee come to our <hi>waſhing,</hi> obſerue theſe <hi>fiue differences</hi> of the <hi>water</hi> of this <hi>Fountaine,</hi> from the <hi>water</hi> of any other <hi>Well</hi> or <hi>Fountaine.</hi> Firſt, One is,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21975:22"/>other <hi>water</hi> can only <hi>waſh</hi> our bodies and outward things; whereas this <hi>water</hi> can <hi>waſh</hi> both bodies and ſoules, the whole man within, as without<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 43. Ezech. 36.25.</note>. Secondly, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other difference is, no other <hi>water</hi> can <hi>waſh</hi> cleane without Sope, Aſhes, Lye, ſome ſcouring balls, or ſuch terſiue helps; but this <hi>Water</hi> of it ſelfe alone <hi>waſheth</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry cleane. Thirdly, No other <hi>water waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> ſo cleane, but there remaineth ſome ſpot, ſtaine, or blot behind, yet this <hi>water</hi> leaueth none; and which more is, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all things fairer and cleaner then they were at firſt. Fourthly, Other <hi>water waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> out onely theſe ſpots that are eaſily done, whereas this <hi>water</hi> worketh with all paine and labour while all be cleane. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, What is made cleane with ordinary <hi>water,</hi> is ſoone fouled againe; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is <hi>waſhed</hi> and made cleane with this <hi>water of Iacobs Well,</hi> ſhall neuer be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed afterwards. Then <hi>will I ſprinkle cleane water vpon you, and yee ſhall be cleane: from all your filthineſſe, and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you. Ezechiel.</hi> 36.25.<note n="d" place="margin">Nunc lauabo, vt rem diuinam faciam. Plaut. in Aulul. act. <hi>5.</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>And where can I beginne better to <hi>waſh</hi> you, then at the <hi>Face,</hi> which is the moſt eminent and apparent part of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21975:22"/>
               <hi>Bodie,</hi> thereon to ſee our ſpots? If any then doth abuſe <hi>Gods Image,</hi> and attempt to controll, or correct his workmanſhip, adding to that <hi>Face,</hi> which <hi>S. Iames</hi> ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>naturall,</hi> the borrowed feature of an artificiall <hi>Face,</hi> ſuffer not mee, but <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> to tell you, that this dawbing, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and parietting of the <hi>Face,</hi> is in ſome reſpect worſe then <hi>Adulterie</hi> it ſelfe.<note n="d" place="margin">Ambroſ. lib. <hi>6</hi> Hexam. c. <hi>8.</hi> Pollux. l <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>16</hi> At hui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſmodi mulieres ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Locrum, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſacien ſed laruam geſtare. itat ur etiam à Coel. Rodig. l <hi>29.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>. For in this foule fact, <hi>perſona vitiatur, the perſon only is polluted,</hi> but in that vngodly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall painting, <hi>natura laeditur, euen na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture herſelfe is more then too much ſpoiled and corrupted. Waſh</hi> off then for ſhame theſe painted colours, and counterfait comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion from thy foule <hi>Face,</hi> with the <hi>water of Jacobs Well,</hi> or elſe they will be rubbed off with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimſtone.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſeuen. <hi>flamma,</hi> ter <hi>aqua,</hi> ter <hi>ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure</hi> luſtrat. Ouid. Metam. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Face</hi> there is a moſt vile, oughly, and deformed blemiſh, called <hi>Impudency,</hi> and it is ſeated on the <hi>Fore-head.</hi> Which although it defileth many a mans <hi>Brow,</hi> yet is it perceiued but of few, and leaſt of thoſe eſpecially, who are moſt infected with it. Contrarie to this is<note n="f" place="margin">Ver cundia cum ſit omnibus aelati us, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, temporibus, &amp; loc is apta, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes iuuenileſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> annos maxim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cet. Ambr. l. <hi>1.</hi> Offic.</note> 
               <hi>Shamefaſtneſſe,</hi> which ſheweth the differing conſtitution of a modeſt, ſober, and wiſe man, from <hi>ſhameleſſe,</hi> ſenſuall, and ſenſeleſſe creatures,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21975:23"/>not worthie the name of men. For as the <hi>Shameleſſe man hath loſt all good maners, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, and ciuilitie,</hi> ſo the <hi>Shamefaſt man</hi> is carefull of his credit, and is afraid of a iuſt reproofe in all his actions<note n="g" place="margin">Ita enim Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hi apud Gellium Noct. Attic. l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Pudor iuſte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuperationis eſt tunor. Quam ſinitionem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen. l. <hi>2.</hi> fidei or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. c. <hi>15.</hi> &amp; Thom. Aquin. <hi>2.2.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>116.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>: and if he faile at any time, in his <hi>thoughts, words,</hi> or <hi>deeds,</hi> a louely bluſh recalleth him into the way of vertue, and ſheweth it ſelfe on his <hi>Front.</hi> There <hi>Shamefaſtneſſe</hi> dwelleth, and may be thus deſcribed, as it was pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or drawen by a cunning hand, aboue foure hundred yeers agoe, and the Table yet ſound, and the colours freſh.<note n="h" place="margin">Vercoundia eſt virga diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae, expugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix malorum, propugnatrix veritatis inna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, ſpecialis glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria conſcientikae, ſame cuſtos, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae decus, virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſedes naturae laus, &amp; inſigne totius honeſti. Bern. ſerm. <hi>86.</hi> in Cant. Vide etiam Alciati <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbl. <hi>196.</hi> in Pudoris ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam.</note> 
               <hi>Shee is the Daughter of Feare,</hi> (euen of that <hi>Feare of God, which is the beginning of Wiſedome</hi>) <hi>the Siſter of Continency, the Diſcouerer of Simplicitie, the Lampe of Chaſtitie, the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Puritie, Conſciences Glorie, Fames Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Lifes Honour, Vertues Seate, Natures Praiſe, Honeſties Cognizence.</hi> Yet as louely as ſhee is, ſhee is but little ſet by in this ſenſuall Age, which hath a <hi>Brow of Braſſe,</hi> there being a number of men &amp; women, whoſe <hi>Fore-head</hi> refuſe to be <hi>Aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This foule vice of <hi>Impudencie,</hi> may bee fitly compared vnto a certaine diſeaſe, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in Latine <hi>Vitiligo,</hi> which<note n="i" place="margin">Apuleius in Magiae ſua.</note> 
               <hi>Apuleius</hi> deſcribes to bee a thicke, groſſe, ſtinking,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21975:23"/>corrupt humour, bred in a mans bodie, and breakes out at firſt on the <hi>Front. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Varro auctor eſt, Titium quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam praetura functum, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morei ſigni ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem habuiſſe propter id vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, Plin. l. <hi>31.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> writes of one named <hi>Titius,</hi> who had beene a <hi>Praetor of Rome,</hi> yet being tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with this euill, was more like an Image of Marble, a blocke, or a ſtone, without all ſenſe and feeling, then like a man. Whereupon <hi>Lucilias</hi> ſaid iuſtly, <hi>haec odioſa mihi <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itiligo eſt.</hi> Conforme to this filthy, loathſome diſeaſe amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, there is a ſicknes that raignes now adayes amongſt vs, which is very like to that in ſenſe and ſound, or in name and effect, called <hi>Vitilitigatio,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſa Litigatio.</hi> No doubt, <hi>Vitiligo,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itilitigatio,</hi> are <hi>two Twinnes,</hi> Daughters begotten of the ſame Father and Mother, both bred vp at one breaſt; which make me ſay plainly, <hi>haec odioſa mihi Vitilitigatio, I loue not Law Suites.</hi> Not that I condemne the Law, or thinke the <hi>Law is ſinne; God forbid: nay the Law is holy, iuſt and good,</hi> as <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. But <hi>Vitilitigato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Hi ſunt qui cauſas proten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt adbibiti, impediunt prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſi, obliuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur locuple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati. Hi ſunt qui emunt lites, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt interceſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, deputant arbitros, iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canda dictant dictato conuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, attrahunt Litigatores, protrahunt audiendos, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahunt tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g nies. Sidon. Apol. ſed ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantiuc<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Orig. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>per i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lud Exo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>8.</hi> Percutiam omnes Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos tuos ranis.</note> 
               <hi>tantum extimeſco,</hi> I am ſo much afraid of <hi>Wrangling Lawyers, Who ſell vs vnder ſinne,</hi> and are not aſhamed of whatſoeuer iniuſtice they haue committed againſt the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and of man. But I wiſh they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21975:24"/>would <hi>waſh</hi> this filthy ſtaine from their <hi>faces</hi> or <hi>foreheads</hi> in time.</p>
            <p>Vnder the <hi>Brow</hi> we ſhould all <hi>waſh</hi> our <hi>Eyes</hi> the ſeate of teares giuing ſo much cauſe of them, and of many <hi>Eye-ſores.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Oculi nos in omnia vitia praecipitant, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, adama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, concupiſcunt, Qumt. decla. <hi>2.</hi> Oculi ſunt in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es.</note>. We ſhould euen <hi>waſh</hi> them with our <hi>Teares,</hi> as the onely <hi>Collyrium</hi> or <hi>Eye-ſalue</hi> to cure all the <hi>ſore Eyes</hi> in this World, and able to wipe all the teares from our <hi>Eyes</hi> in the World to<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 7.17.</note> come.</p>
            <p>Next to our <hi>Eyes,</hi> wee muſt <hi>waſh</hi> our <hi>Eares:</hi> for the <hi>Eye</hi> and <hi>Eare,</hi> are like <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Leui, brethren in euill, Vaſa iniquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis bellantia, Inſtruments of crueltie in their habitation</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 49.5.</note> of corrupted <hi>Eares</hi> I may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pannell a whole <hi>Iurie,</hi> yet not one of them good or true. As <hi>Midas</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Auriculas Midae quis non habet? Perſ. Sat. <hi>1.</hi> Sic de Petron. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eares; Malchu's Eares,</hi> who will heare but with the <hi>left Fare, Peter</hi> hauing cut off the <hi>right</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Qui ſtatuit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liquid parte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auditâ alterâ, Aequum licet ſtatuerit haud aequus tamen, Sen. in Medea.</note> 
               <hi>Eare; Athenian Eares; curious; cryticall;</hi> and <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall Eares, &amp;c.</hi> which all ſhould well be <hi>waſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo ſhould our <hi>Mouth</hi> bee well <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</hi> as full of Vlcers, Cankers, Swellings and Sores. Therein is poyſon of <hi>Aſpes vnder the,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 58.41.</note> 
               <hi>Lips; Teeth are as ſwords; jawes as</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 30.14.</note> 
               <hi>Kniues; the Tongue can no man tame, it is an vnruly member which defileth the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21975:24"/>and ſetteth on fire the courſe of</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iames 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>nature, the Throat is an open</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iſay 59.7.</note> 
               <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire all to be throughly <hi>waſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Mouth</hi> be thus <hi>foule,</hi> and needeth to bee <hi>waſhed</hi> throughly, what requireth the <hi>Heat, out of the abundance whereof the Mouth</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 12.34. Marke 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeaketh?</hi> Out of this euill trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nothing but euill can bee produced. The <hi>Heart is wicked and deceitfull aboue all</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ier. 17.9.</note> 
               <hi>things:</hi> who know it but <hi>God the Searcher of all</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> 
               <hi>hearts,</hi> which prohibits me further inueſtigation of her wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will waſh my hands in innocencie then O Lord, and ſo will I goe to thine</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 26.6.</hi> Date manibus famuli limpha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Et manibus pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſumite Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis aquam.</note> 
               <hi>Altar.</hi> Thus the <hi>Diuine</hi> ſhould <hi>waſh</hi> his <hi>hands</hi>-with <hi>King Dauid, Pſal.</hi> 26.6. and euery <hi>Lawyer</hi> ſhould ſay with the <hi>Prophet Eſay</hi> 33.15. <hi>I will ſhake mine hands from holding of bribes.</hi> Foras <hi>Saint Bernard</hi> ſayes, <hi>magnum eſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſeculari mundas habere manus, It is much for a Layman to keepe his hands cleane,</hi> ſo (mee thinkes) a <hi>Clergiemans hands</hi> ſhould not be foule any wayes.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe wee muſt all <hi>waſh</hi> our <hi>feet</hi> as well as our <hi>hands;</hi> otherwiſe they cannot be kept cleane. For euen the <hi>feet</hi> of the beſt and godlieſt men in this life, are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dabled or defiled, trampling in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21975:25"/>
A <hi>Miniſter</hi> in his moſt <hi>Angelicall calling,</hi> may gather ſoyle in his<note n="q" place="margin">Philoſophi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquiores, qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> doctrinam eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſequuti ſunt, pedes pro contemperſſima parte poſuerunt, eſſe<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in anima pedes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>affectus voluptarios Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neree mollitrdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni mancipatos.</note> 
               <hi>feet</hi> if not by his <hi>ignorance</hi> or <hi>negigence,</hi> yet through the dirt of the World; therefore he <hi>muſt ſhake the duſt of his feet</hi> before hee goe into the Pulpit. <hi>Magiſtrates, Iuſtices,</hi> and <hi>others in Authoritie</hi> are to bee feared and ſuſpected they are foule in their <hi>feet:</hi> for though no corruption (perhaps) cleaue to their owne <hi>hands</hi> or <hi>feet,</hi> yet may it bee brought into the houſe, by ſome dirtie complayner or other; by ſome clay Clyant, and foule cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: or elſe priuately fetched in by ſome rigorous Seriant, by ſome craftie Clarke, or cunning ſeruant, walking in foule wayes. <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> in their Trades cannot ſweepe their ſhoppes ſo cleane, but they leaue ſome duſt of deceit, ſome ſlurtiſh corner of double-dealing<note n="r" place="margin">Qui cauet ne decipiatur vix cauet, etiam cum cauet, &amp; cum cauiſſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ſeapius au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor captus eſt, Plaut. in Caſt. Nam-Pleniùs aequo laudat vae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales qui vult extrudere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Horat. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt.</note> which are to to be wiped and rubbed from their <hi>feet,</hi> (that is to ſay properly) <hi>from their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Quis metus aut pudor eſt vnquam propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantis auari, Iuuen. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>. For the <hi>feet</hi> are taken for the baſe and earthly <hi>affections</hi> of the minde, which moued <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> to ſay, <hi>Pes meus, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus meus; eò feror quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> feror</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">S. Aug. Homil. <hi>50.</hi> Tom. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>. And in this ſenſe, <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Simon Peter, hee that is waſhed, needeth not ſaue to waſh his feet, but is cleane euery whit, Iohn</hi> 13.10.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21975:25"/>
Let vs then <hi>waſh our feet,</hi> I meane, the <hi>affections,</hi> paſſions and perturbations of the minde; yea, the <hi>whole man</hi> within and without, vp and downe, to and fro. For yee know, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>as non poteſt bene lauari, niſi concutiatur, niſi fex expellatur, niſi poſtea mundum ſeruetur. God</hi> when he threatned to <hi>waſh</hi> well the <hi>Veſſell</hi> of the <hi>Earth</hi> to make it cleane from imperfections, hee ſaid by his <hi>Prophet Iſaiah</hi> 24.19. <hi>Confracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one confringetur terra, contritione conteretur, commotione commouebitur, agitatione agitabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. The earth is vtterly broken downe, the earth is cleane diſſolued, the carth is moued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, the earth ſhall reele to and fro, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make it cleane and neate. Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> was willed to <hi>waſh</hi> himſelfe ſeuen times in <hi>Iordan,</hi> and that rather for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and example, then for his owne benefit. For his ſickneſſe was onely a <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie</hi> in the bodie, where our ſoules and bodies are both leprous with ſinne: and if he but for one <hi>Leproſie waſhed himſelfe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times,</hi> how much more ought we eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time we ſinne to bee ſorie for it and if wee doe not <hi>waſh</hi> our ſelues <hi>ſeuen times</hi> for <hi>ſeuen ſinnes,</hi> ſeeing the moſt iuſt of vs all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21975:26"/>(as <hi>Salomon</hi> witneſſeth) may <hi>ſeuen times fall in one day, Prou.</hi> 24.16.</p>
            <p>Oh how ought wee then to <hi>waſh</hi> and <hi>bath</hi> our ſelues, and that euen <hi>ſeuentie times ſeuen</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth. 18.22</hi> Hoc eſt, <hi>490.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed melius Maldonat in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, vicibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerabiliter innumerabilibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Toties quoties. Aug. ſerm. <hi>15.</hi> de verbis Dom.</note>; whether we looke vpward towards <hi>God</hi> whom we haue offended, or downward vpon Hell, which wee haue deſerued, or backward vpon our ſinnes committed, or forward vpon iudgement to bee feared, or without vs vpon the deceitfull world which wee haue loued, or within vs vpon our polluted conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in aſſurance of heart, our ſinnes thus throughly waſhed, are purged and made cleane with the pure and liuing <hi>Water of</hi> Iacobs <hi>Well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now</hi> Iacobs <hi>Well was there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold now for our <hi>Application,</hi> and <hi>third ſenſe,</hi> how my <hi>Lord Archbiſhop Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots Conduit</hi> ſorteth <hi>by Analogie</hi> with Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs <hi>Well,</hi> and what proportion or corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondencie is betweene them two, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>fiue former occurrences in the letter;</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Non tota res totae rei neceſſe eſt ſimilis ſit: ſed ad ipſum ad quod confertur, ſimilitudinem habeat oportet, Author ad He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. lib <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially in theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will ſerue moſt fitly for our beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21975:26"/>
As <hi>firſt</hi> conſider <hi>(Situm)</hi> your <hi>Conduit is ſeated in the midſt of this Citie, betweene two famous Churches, though ſomewhat neerer to the one, then to the other, and that rather done of purpoſe,</hi> then by chance in my conceite.<note n="y" place="margin">Vrbs peruetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta proculdubio illaſtris, Nec a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deo magna (vt inquit Malmeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burienſis) nec exiliter parua, quae &amp; terrae poſitione ſoli af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finis maxima v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate, &amp; inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro murorum ambitu, fluuijs irrigua, nemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate inclita, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea Maris vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinitate piſcium foecunda, &amp;c.</note> Wherein looke to the <hi>Citie</hi> it ſelfe, and you will ſee it is builded in the ſweeteſt Aire, betweene two little Hils, <hi>amidſt the richeſt ſoyle aboue the Valley of fatneſſe, Larga vbi foecunda rerum vndat copia cornu;</hi> where is <hi>Gods</hi> plentie without ploughing or ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reaping or keeping; you are fed like the fowles of the Aire, and grow vp as the Lillies of the field, a thouſand times more happily, then if Corne grew at your doores, or Cattell grazed in your ſtreets, neere enough the benefits, and farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from the dangers of the Seas, in the <hi>beſt place</hi> of the chiefeſt <hi>Shire</hi> of this <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,</hi> euen in<note n="z" place="margin">Haec tantum alias inter ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put extulit vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Quantum inter viburna Cupreſſi.</note> 
               <hi>Canterburie,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> or <hi>Head-Towne</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> if not of <hi>All Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In this <hi>Citie</hi> there bee <hi>Hospitals</hi> and <hi>Almeſ-houſes</hi> for the entertainment of old, aged, decayed folkes, and a Nurſerie of young Orphans; a <hi>Bridewell</hi> for the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and employment of idle perſons; a <hi>Kings Free Schoole,</hi> where youth may drinke in the firſt liquour of wholſome
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21975:27"/>Learning; and amongſt many other <hi>Workes of Charitie,</hi> now heere is <hi>Iacobs Well,</hi> or <hi>Abbots Conduit,</hi> flowing forth abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly wholſome and good water, <hi>To the Vſe of this Citie;</hi> But aboue all other <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents,</hi> here is the <hi>Cathedrall</hi> and <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politicall</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Chriſti Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum in medio quaſi vrbis ſinu, tanta maiſtate, vt ſe in Coelum erigit, vt procul etiam intuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m incutiat. Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Peregri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Religionis ergo.</note> 
               <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di operis, Beda</note> 
               <hi>which is a wonderfull piece of worke to the beholders;</hi> and neere vnto it, within the walls of the <hi>Citie,</hi> there are <hi>Twelue Pariſh Churches;</hi> wherein weekly on the Sabbath and Holidayes, (as daily in the <hi>Cathedrall Church,</hi>) the freſh ſprings of our hope and comfort, by <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and <hi>Preaching</hi> the <hi>Sacred Word of God,</hi> as by ſtreames and ſo many <hi>Conduits</hi> doe continually refreſh and <hi>make glad the Citie of God.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">O ſortu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atos nimium ſua ſi bona norint Cantuarienſes.</note> Oh happy then are you of this Citie, if you knew your owne happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe!</p>
            <p>Secondly, This <hi>Conduit</hi> is built <hi>within the City,</hi> and not <hi>without the Towne;</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hinc com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiùs mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, ſuauius, minore<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſumpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ciues victitant, nec iam facile, ſiti cogente, in hoſtrum poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem incident cum obſidentur.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to your greater <hi>Vſe,</hi> eaſe and delight in time of Peace, and to your leſſe danger in time of Warres. For the<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 26.15.</note> 
               <hi>Philistins</hi> could not ſhew their ſpight in any thing ſo much to the <hi>Patriarchs, Abraham, Iſaak</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> as to ſtop vp their <hi>Wels.</hi> Neither (that wee may ſpeake of latter times) did
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21975:27"/>the<note n="f" place="margin">Sleidan. com. <hi>18</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Romiſh Philiſtin</hi> in any thing ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcouer his malice, as when hee ſent Poyſoners to corrupt the <hi>Wels of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant countries in Germanie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, And this<note n="g" place="margin">Lauda &amp; la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare filia Sion, quia ecce ego venio, &amp; habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabo in medio tui, ait Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. <hi>Zach. 2.10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conduit is ſealed in the midſt of the Citie;</hi> thereby to conuey more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently the current or ſtreames thereof, vnto the chiefe ſtreets of the <hi>Towne,</hi> and there to ſerue euery man more readily to his priuate <hi>Vſe.</hi> In this point, <hi>Art</hi> imitated <hi>Nature,</hi> which affecteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the <hi>midſt,</hi> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> is ſet in the <hi>midſt</hi> of the <hi>Planets,</hi> and the <hi>Heart</hi> as the <hi>Fountaine</hi> of life and heate, is placed in the <hi>midſt</hi> of the members.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In that it is erected<note n="h" place="margin">Vide quid de hoc dicat Bellar. lib. de Beatitud. Sanctorum ca. vlt. §. Respondeo Sanctor. Baron. Eccle. ſiaſt. Annal. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> ad an. <hi>290.</hi> ex editione Romana.</note> 
               <hi>between two famous Churches,</hi> named <hi>Saint Georges</hi> and <hi>Saint Andrew's,</hi> (both vvorthy <hi>Patterns</hi> it not <hi>Patrons</hi> of theſe <hi>two mightie Nations England and Scotland;</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Nos gentes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guimus, Deo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na domus eſt mundus hic to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus. Minut. Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</note> thereby to teach vs, that as heretofore theſe two <hi>Kingdomes</hi> liued in one Continent (although much different by their fatall diuiſion,) both by Sea deuided from people adiacent, both of <hi>one Language,</hi> both <hi>worſhipping one God,</hi> both of <hi>one Faith,</hi> both of <hi>one Baptiſme,</hi> and both of <hi>one Communion,</hi> ſo now (pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God) they liue as <hi>one People,</hi> vnder
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21975:28"/>
               <hi>one King,</hi> and <hi>one Law.</hi> Yea, as <hi>Water</hi> is a ſymbole of Amitie, Peace and Concord, ſo the <hi>ſeating of this Conduit, betweene theſe two Churches,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iam verò vt quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nobiſcum maximè amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſponſione, foedere, pactione coniuncta eſt, ita nobis maximè communionem beneficiorum, praemiorumque ciuitatis conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere videatur, Cic. pro Cornel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>albo.</note> ſignifieth wee are not to build vp a <hi>Babylon</hi> through our confuſion and former Feuds, but to reedifie <hi>one Church in one Vnion and Communion euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, In that this <hi>Conduit is ſeated ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what the neerer to Saint Andrewes Church then to Saint Georges,</hi> it is (in my opinion) to reueale that old Prophecie foretold of the <hi>Patriarch Iacob,</hi> now accompliſhed in our <hi>King Iames</hi> For although his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie is not halfe a birth, as was <hi>Iacob,</hi> but one onely Sonne, cutting ſhort thereby all diſpute of <hi>Titles</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 25.23. Rom. 9.9. &amp; 12</note> 
               <hi>and Birthright</hi> with <hi>Elder Eſaues;</hi> yet as <hi>God ſaid to Rebecca, two Nations are in thy wombe, and the one ſhall be mightier then the other, and the elder ſhall ſerue the younger:</hi> ſo in the perſon of our <hi>Princely Iacob,</hi> were two <hi>Nations</hi> borne, to wit, <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> whereof the elder may bee ſaid in ſome ſort, to ſerue the younger, in ſo farre as <hi>England</hi> being<note n="m" place="margin">In hoc diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d coetera poenè gemelli.</note> 
               <hi>Maior</hi> or <hi>Melior,</hi> is now come vnder his <hi>Maieſties</hi> gouernment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then of only <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſo <hi>Minor.</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21975:28"/>Howſoeuer this obſeruation holdeth in the generall, it is certaine,<note n="n" place="margin">Vſus commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Aquarum eſt &amp;c. Ouid. Metam <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> this <hi>Conduit</hi> is patent or open in particular vnto<note n="o" place="margin">Tros Tiriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <hi>ſibi</hi> nullo diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine habetur.</note> 
               <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> as to <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and to all Forrainers or Strangers, as to the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of this Citie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider <hi>[Structuram,] the Worke it ſelfe,</hi> in <hi>Matter</hi> and in <hi>Forme;</hi> in the <hi>Principall</hi> and in the <hi>Acceſſorie,</hi> and yee will find them wholly <hi>To the Vſe of the Citie.</hi> Gaze not only vpon it, as little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren looke vpon their painted Booke, but thinke, as there was no Pinne in <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple, which was not ſeruiceable to ſome holy Vſe,<note n="p" place="margin">In omnibus Timan this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus plus intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligitu ſemper quam pingitur: &amp; cum ars ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſit, ingenium tamen vltra ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temeſt. Plin. lib. <hi>35.</hi> c <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> ſo is there not any thing in this <hi>Conduit,</hi> which is not profitable for our inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fabrike</hi> or <hi>Architecture</hi> it ſelfe is<note n="q" place="margin">Horat. de Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Poet.</note> 
               <hi>Monumentum aere</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Annare &amp; perennare in perpetuas aeler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitates <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>perennius,</hi> a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more durable then braſſe: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Monuments are ſo called, as <hi>monentia mentem,</hi> monitors of the mind, let me be ſo bold as to admoniſh you (Citizens of Canterburie) that you bee thankfull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our <hi>Benefactor;</hi> at leaſt, beware that you be not thought vnthankfull.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ingratus eſt qui beneficium: ſe accepiſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat quod acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, Ingratus eſt qui diſſimulat, Ingratus eſt qui non reddit; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratùs omnium qui oblitus eſt. Seneca <hi>3.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n. ficijs.</note> 
               <hi>Hee is vnthankfull</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) <hi>who is vnmindfull of a benefit which he hath receiued; vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21975:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21975:29"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:21975:30"/>that requites it not; vnthankfull that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth it; but moſt vnthankfull that diſſembleth it.</hi> Such is this <hi>fauour,</hi> that wee can neuer requite it, nor can we <hi>diſſemble</hi> it <hi>(the very ſtones of the walls of it will crie out, and the water of it will murmur and mutter againſt vs)</hi> yet let vs neuer <hi>forget</hi> the <hi>Gift</hi> nor the <hi>Giuer.</hi> Let it not grieue vs to ſpeake good of his <hi>Name,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Non mibi ſi cunctos Helicon indulgeat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, Et ſuperet Pymplea ſitim, large<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> voluntis, Vngula ſedet Equi, reſeret<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rcana pudicos Phoemonoe fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes</note> nay ſeeing our words are not able ſufficiently to expreſſe his praiſe, <hi>(quid niſi vota ſuperſunt?)</hi> let vs pray for his health and proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Another monition is, that you of beſt meanes or wealth would open your Wels to the<note n="u" place="margin">Rabbini ege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; paupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem de inſirmo &amp; quaſi aegri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine attenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exponunt, non de vulgatis pauperibus. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> enim egenus, otiam apud nos ſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur pro infirmo, vnde apud E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piph. &amp; Can. <hi>8.</hi> Chaloedonenſ. Concilii <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hoſpitium pauperum &amp; in firmorum.</note> poore members of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> If you cannot build a <hi>Conduit,</hi> yet you can refreſh the poore. And you know if our <hi>Sauiour</hi> promiſed a reward for a cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, giuen in ſeaſon for his ſake,<note n="x" place="margin">Si poculum frigidae aquae iuſtificat miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordem, quanta retributio om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia diſtribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem pauſeribas excipiet? Nilus Epiſc. admo <hi>185</hi>
               </note> what is a cup o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cold water in compariſon of a faire coſtly <hi>Conduit</hi> full of good water? When any of the Poore ſit hungrie, thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, wearie or cold at your <hi>Wells</hi> or doores, pretend not a <hi>Statute</hi> to ſpare your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the <hi>woman of Samaria</hi> refuſed wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> to ſaue her paines. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the waters; for thou ſhall find it after many dayes.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Si bene quid facias fac c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò: nam citò factii gratum erit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratum gratia tarda ſacit.</note> If thou intendeſt any
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21975:30"/>good worke for a publike benefit, to the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> delay it not, nor remit it not to your <hi>Heires</hi> or <hi>Executors,</hi> leſt you ſhould ſeeme to dare truſt them better with your goods, then your ſelues, and ſo conſequently, the worke prooue theirs rather then yours.<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>God loueth a liuing ſacrifice, and</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>a cheerfull giuer:</hi> and it hath beene an old rule in liberalitie, <hi>He giueth twice that giueth quickly,</hi> whereas ſlowe benefits argue vnwillingneſſe, and loſe their worth. Let vs doe good then in our owne time, that we may haue ſome pleaſure or profit of it our ſelues, and ſo proue the ſonnes of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and imitators of my <hi>Lord Arch-biſhop Abbots</hi> in his good workes.</p>
            <p>Loe<note n="c" place="margin">Iam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> opus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egit, quod nec Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ira, nec. ignes, Nec. pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ferrum, nec edax abolere vetuſtas. Ouid. in fine Metam.</note> 
               <hi>His Grace</hi> hath accompliſhed this his charitable <hi>Worke,</hi> and other good <hi>Deeds</hi> in his owne dayes, which neither time nor malice can euer aboliſh or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh. For the <hi>Materials</hi> of this <hi>Conduit</hi> are durable; the <hi>Forme</hi> of it <hi>Foure-ſquare;</hi> the <hi>Water-cockes</hi> about it, in <hi>number fiue;</hi> and the <hi>fiue lines for Inſcription on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpice,</hi> are of <hi>fine Gold;</hi> all which are ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall, and ſignifie<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>his memorie ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for euer.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Reuel. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Now, when <hi>timber, ſtones,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21975:31"/>brickes,</hi> and <hi>bookes,</hi> ſhall all be wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and diſſolued, the <hi>Bookes</hi> of Heauen ſhall be opened, where all the <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>His pious workes,</hi> are written in a moſt inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leble Character, and ſhall be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an vnualuable reward, euen an eternall <hi>Crowne</hi> of glorie. Meane time, all you who heare me this day, let my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell bee acceptable vnto you: conſider, I beſeech you, that onely your <hi>good workes,</hi> will be your companions to Heauen, they ſhall be your honour in life; your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in death, and your Crowne at the laſt <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke likewiſe to the<note n="f" place="margin">Pictoribus utque Poëtis, Quodlibet au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi, ſemper fuit aequa pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas. Horat. in Arte Poët.</note> 
               <hi>painting</hi> vpon, and about this <hi>Conduit for ornament,</hi> and you may perceiue, <hi>Paludamenta haec,</hi> theſe <hi>rich Coates at Armès</hi> tell you,<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 49.9.</note> that <hi>Iacob</hi> was the firſt Inuen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of <hi>Hem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rie,</hi> in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning <hi>Armes,</hi> vnto <hi>his twelue ſonnes the Patriarchs:</hi> as to<note n="h" place="margin">Arma anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua manus, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, denteſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fuere. Lucret.</note> 
               <hi>Iudah</hi> a <hi>Lyon;</hi> to <hi>Dan</hi> a <hi>Serpent;</hi> to <hi>Neph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ali</hi> an <hi>Hinde;</hi> to <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> a <hi>Wolfe;</hi> and ſo to the reſt.<note n="i" place="margin">Lege cautum eſt, ſolum Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratorem conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere poſſe, ne quis ſit mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s qui non eſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> genere Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. Ius Nobilitandi ad ſolum Regempertinet. Ibid.</note> Hereby alſo ſignifying none ſhould preſume to aſſume vnto himſelfe <hi>Armes,</hi> but expect them of the <hi>Kings Maieſtie</hi> onely, as the <hi>Princely Iacob</hi> within his Dominious. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, if men <hi>buy</hi> them, and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21975:31"/>
               <hi>vnworthie</hi> of them, <hi>quid tanto hia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu dignum?</hi> they are to bee mocked for them; and their <hi>Armories</hi> are no more to bee eſteemed, then a <hi>painted Signe</hi> before an <hi>Inne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Virtus colen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt, non Imae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go virtutis. Nec aliud eſt col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re virtutem niſi eam comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere animo, &amp; tenere. Lactant. lib. de falſa Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note>Aboue the <hi>Armes</hi> you may obſerue the ſpeaking power of <hi>Pictures;</hi> and the liuely <hi>Images</hi> of the <hi>ſeuen Vertues;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ruder multitude may euen by their ſight learne to know, and to embrace <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</hi> I am deceiued if any other thing or courſe could haue beene <hi>vſed</hi> more like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſitly to preuaile IN VSVM CI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VITATIS <hi>Cantuariae, to the Vſe and Benefit of this Citie,</hi> then theſe <hi>Images.</hi> For herein, the groſſe conceit is led on with pleaſure, and informed while it feeles nothing but delight. And if<note n="l" place="margin">Signa propter imperitum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus formata re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert ex Pagano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſententia. Arnob. lib. <hi>6.</hi> Dicebant n. illi Imagines eſſe veluti Libros Plebeculae: Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius praeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim apud Euſeb. lib. <hi>3</hi> de praepar. ad Euangel. Segnius irritant animos demiſſa per aures. Quàm quae ſunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t coulis ſubiecta fidelibus. Horat. vbi ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Pictures</hi> haue beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the Bookes of <hi>Idiots,</hi> behold here the benefit of an <hi>Image,</hi> without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. It is no ſhame for vs to learne wit of <hi>Heathens;</hi> neither is it materiall in whoſe Schoole wee take out a good. Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: yea, it is more ſhame not to follow their good, then not to leade them better. Proue<note n="m" place="margin">Longum iter eſt per praecepta, breue &amp; eſſicax per exampla. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec epiſt. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> your ſelues then <hi>Wiſe men, Iuſt, Strong,</hi> and <hi>Sober,</hi> conforme to theſe <hi>foure Figures,</hi> or <hi>Cardinall Vertues, Prudence, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21975:32"/>Fortitude, Temperance,</hi> thus placed in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Next to them abide</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Fides appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata eſt abeo quod fit duae ſyllabae, quarum prima eſt à fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto, ſecunda à Deo. Dicis quod crodis, fac ergo quod dicis &amp; fides eſt. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. ſerm <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Faith,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Idem de Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritu &amp; Litera. Magis videtur Dei fil us qui nouit à quo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, quod non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum habet, quâm qui ſibi tribuit quod habet.</note> 
               <hi>Hope, and</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Charitas di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur à Graeco <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quod eſt gratia, lepos, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micitia; cù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> enim cognatio i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter bomines vna ſit, vita<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpecies, nihil magis decens eſt hac hominum mutua Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Charitas Via Dei ad homines eſt, &amp; via ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis ad Deum. Auguſtin. ibid. de Spiritu &amp; Litera.</note> 
               <hi>Charitie; but the greateſt of theſe three is Charitie.</hi> When the <hi>three Goddeſſes,</hi> ſay the Poets, ſtroue for the <hi>golden Ball, Paris</hi> adiudged it to the <hi>Queene of Loue.</hi> Loe here are <hi>three</hi> celeſtiall <hi>Graces,</hi> in an holy emulation, if I may ſo ſay, ſtriuing for the chiefdome, <hi>S. Paul</hi> giues it to <hi>Loue: The greateſt of theſe is Charitie.</hi> And me thinks theſe <hi>Three Theologicall Vertues,</hi> may fitly be compared to the three great Feaſts of the yeere: <hi>Eaſter, Whitſontide,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas. Faith,</hi> like <hi>Eaſter,</hi> beleeues <hi>Chriſt</hi> dead for our ſinnes, and riſen againe for our Iuſtification. <hi>Hope,</hi> like <hi>Pentecost,</hi> waites for the comming of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> to bring vs to Heauen. And <hi>Charitie</hi> lookes like <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> full of <hi>Loue</hi> to our <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;</hi> full of <hi>Hoſpitalitie</hi> to <hi>Strangers;</hi> and full of <hi>Charitie</hi> to the <hi>Poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end and purpoſe, there is a little <hi>Bell</hi> hung vp in a Tower aboue all theſe <hi>ſeuen <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues,</hi> thereby to ring into our eares on euery market day this aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Remember the Poore,</hi> or bee <hi>charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> In this ſenſe, that <hi>Bell Anagogically</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21975:32"/>may bee called<note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod. 28.34.</note> 
               <hi>Aarons Bell,</hi> thus ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note n="t" place="margin">Dictis factae praecedunt, imo ſine factis dicta nihil proſunt. Nam ideo &amp; Dominus fieri voluit, ſic doce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, ne ſine bono opere verborum inutilis eſſet &amp; ſuperſtitioſa ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatio. Ambroſ. ſerm. <hi>76.</hi> Qui dicica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; non faciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſunt Aera ſonantia &amp; cymbala tinni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia, <hi>1. Corin. 13.1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>good words</hi> to <hi>good workes,</hi> or <hi>faire ſpeeches</hi> to <hi>vertuous actions;</hi> and ſo a <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bell</hi> and a <hi>Pomegranate, a Pomegranate</hi> and a <hi>Golden Bell,</hi> that as the delight and pleaſure of the one ſerue to the ſight, ſo the ſound of the other ſhould pierce into the eare.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 5.19.</note>
               <hi>Whoſoeuer ſhall doe and ſay theſe things</hi> (ſaith our Lord) <hi>the ſame ſhall bee called great in the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> And as Saint<note n="x" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.4 10 &amp; 11.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid in his firſt Epiſtle the fift Chapter and fourth Verſe, <hi>Yee ſhall receiue a</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pulchra A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maranti Coronae in Coelis repoſita illi qui ſe rectë geſſerit, Clem. Alex. l. <hi>2.</hi> paedag. <hi>214.</hi> alludens ad hanc Petri immarceſſibilem gloriae Coronam, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſiquidem &amp; herbam &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marceſſibilem ſignificat: de hac fuſius, Dioſcorid. &amp; Plin. lib. <hi>21.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Crowne of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> as in token thereof heere a <hi>Gilded Crowne in the top of this Conduit.</hi> Therefore,<note n="z" place="margin">Deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt Tertull. ad Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. c. <hi>3.</hi> Bonum Agonem ſubituri eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> quo Ago<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ethetes Deus vnus eſt, Xyſtarches Spiritus Sanctus, Corona Aeternitatis brauium, Angelicae ſubſtantiae, Politia in Coelis, gloria in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula ſaeculorum.</note> final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to conclude, <hi>the God of all grace who hath called vs into his eternall glory by Chriſt Ieſus, after that yee haue ſuffered awhile, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen, ſettle you. To him be glory and dominion for euer and euer.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
